The following content is provided under a
Creative
Commons license. Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer high quality
educational
resources for free. To make a donation or
to view
additional materials from hundreds of MIT
courses,
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at ocw.mit.edu.
Yesterday we saw how to define double integrals
and how to
start computing them in terms of x and y coordinates.
We have defined the double integral over a
region R and
plane of a function f of x, y dA.
You cannot hear me? Is the sound working?
Can you hear me in the back now? Can we make
the sound louder?
Does this work? People are not hearing me
in
the back. Is it better?
People are still saying make it louder.
Is it better? OK.
Great. Thanks.
That's not a reason to start chatting with
your friends.
Thanks. When we have a region in the x,
y plane and we have a function of x and y,
we are defining the double integral of f over
this region
by taking basically the sum of the values
of a function
everywhere in here times the area element.
And the definition, actually, is we split
the region into
lots of tiny little pieces, we multiply the
value of a
function at the point times the area of a
little piece and we
sum that everywhere. And we have seen,
actually, how to compute these things as iterated
integrals.
First, integrating over dy and then over dx,
or the other way around. One example that
we did,
in particular, was to compute the double
integral of a quarter of a unit disk.
That was the region where x squared plus y
squared is less
than one and x and y are positive, of one
minus x squared
minus y squared dA. Well, hopefully,
I kind of convinced you that we can do it
using enough trig and
substitutions and so on, but it is not very
pleasant.
And the reason for that is that using x and
y coordinates here
does not seem very appropriate. In fact, we
can use polar
coordinates instead to compute this double
integral.
Remember that polar coordinates are about
replacing x and y as
coordinates for a point on a plane by instead
r,
which is the distance from the origin to a
point,
and theta, which is the angle measured
counterclockwise from the positive x-axis.
In terms of r and theta, you have x equals
r cosine
theta, y equals r sine theta. The claim is
we are able,
actually, to do double integrals in polar
coordinates.
We just have to learn how to. Just to draw
a quick picture --
When we were integrating in x, y coordinates,
in rectangular coordinates, we were slicing
our region by
gridlines that were either horizontal or vertical.
And we used that to set up the iterated integral.
And we said dA became dx dy or dy dx.
Now we are going to actually integrate, in
terms of the polar
coordinates, r and theta. Let's say we will
integrate in
the order with r first and then theta.
That is the order that makes the most sense
usually when you
do polar coordinates. What does that mean?
It means that we will first focus on a slice
where we fix
the value of theta and we will let r vary.
That means we fix a direction, we fix a ray
out from the
origin in a certain direction. And we will
travel along this
ray and see which part of it, which values
of r are in our
region. Here it will be actually pretty
easy because r will just start at zero, and
you will have to
stop when you exit this quarter disk.
Well, what is the equation of this circle
in polar
coordinates? It is just r equals one.
So, we will stop when r reaches one.
But what about theta? Well, the first ray
that we
might want to consider is the one that goes
along the x-axis.
That is when theta equals zero. And we will
stop when theta
reaches pi over two because we don't care
about the rest of the
disk. We only care about the first
quadrant. We will stop at pi over two.
Now, there is a catch, though, which is that
dA is not
dr d theta. Let me explain to you why.
Let's say that we are slicing. What it means
is we are cutting
our region into little pieces that are the
elementary,
you know, what corresponds to a small
rectangle in the x, y coordinate system,
here would be actually a little piece of circle
between a given
radius r and r plus delta r. And given between
an angle
theta and theta plus delta theta.
I need to draw, actually, a bigger picture
of
that because it makes it really hard to read.
Let's say that I fix an angle theta and a
slightly different
one where I have added delta theta to it.
And let's say that I have a radius r and I
add delta r to
it. Then I will have a little piece
of x, y plane that is in here. And I have
to figure out what
is its area? What is delta A for this guy?
Well, let's see. This guy actually,
you know, if my delta r and delta theta are
small enough,
it will almost look like a rectangle.
It is rotated, but it is basically a
rectangle. I mean these sides,
of course, are curvy, but they are short enough
and
it is almost straight. The area here should
be this
length times that length. Well, what is this
length?
That one is easy. It is delta r.
What about that length? Well, it is not delta
theta.
It is something slightly different.
It is a piece of a circle of radius r corresponding
to angle
delta theta, so it is r delta theta.
So, times r delta theta. That means now,
even if we shrink things and take smaller
and smaller
regions, dA is going to be r dr d theta.
That is an important thing to remember.
When you integrate in polar coordinates, you
just set up
your bounds in terms of r and theta, but you
replace dA by r
dr d theta, not just dr d theta. And then,
of course,
we have some function that we are integrating.
Let's say that I call that thing f then it
is the same f
that I put up here. Concretely, how do I do
it here?
Well, my function f was given as one minus
x squared minus y
squared. And I would like to switch that
to polar coordinates. I want to put r and
theta in
there. Well, I have formulas for x and
y in polar coordinates so I could just replace
x squared by
r squared cosine squared theta, y squared
by r squared sine
squared theta. And that works just fine.
But maybe you can observe that this is x squared
plus y
squared. It is just the square of a
distance from the origin, so that is just
r squared.
That is a useful thing. You don't strictly
need it,
but it is much faster if you see this right
away.
It saves you writing down a sine and a cosine.
Now we just end up with the integral from
zero to pi over
two, integral from zero to one of one minus
r squared r dr d
theta. Now, if I want to compute this
integral, so let's first do the inner integral.
If I integrate r minus r cubed, I will get
r squared over two
minus r squared over four between zero and
one.
And then I will integrate d theta.
What is this equal to? Well, for r equals
one you get
one-half minus one-quarter, which is going
to be just
one-quarter. And when you plug in zero you
get zero. So, it is the integral from
zero to pi over two of one-quarter d theta.
And that just integrates to one-quarter times
pi over two,
which is pi over eight. That is a lot easier
than the
way we did it yesterday. Well, here we were
lucky.
I mean usually you will switch to polar coordinates
either
because the region is easier to set up.
Here it is indeed easier to set up because
the bounds became
very simple. We don't have that square root
of one minus x squared anymore. Or because
the integrant
becomes much simpler. Here our function,
well, it is not very complicated in x,
y coordinates, but it is even simpler in r
theta coordinates. Here we were very lucky.
In general, there is maybe a trade off.
Maybe it will be easier to set up bounds but
maybe the function
will become harder because it will have all
these sines and
cosines in it. If our function had been just
x, x is very easy in x, y coordinates.
Here it becomes r cosine theta. That means
you will have a
little bit of trig to do in the integral.
Not a very big one, not a very complicated
integral, but imagine it could get potentially
much harder.
Anyway, that is double integrals in polar
coordinates.
And the way you set up the bounds in general,
well, in 99% of the cases you will integrate
over r first.
What you will do is you will look for a given
theta what are
the bounds of r to be in the region.
What is the portion of my ray that is in the
given region?
And then you will put bounds for theta.
But conceptually it is the same as before.
Instead of slicing horizontally or vertically,
we slice radially. We will do more examples
in a
bit. Any questions about this or the
general method? Yes?
That is a very good question. Why do I measure
the length
inside instead of outside? Which one do I
want?
This one. Here I said this side is r
delta theta. I could have said,
actually, r delta theta is the length here.
Here it is slightly more, r plus delta r times
delta
theta. But, if delta r is very small
compared to r, then that is almost the same
thing. And this is an approximation
anyway. I took this one because it
gives me the simpler formula. If you take
the limit as delta
r turns to zero then the two things become
the same anyway.
The length, whether you put r or r plus delta
r in here,
doesn't matter anymore. If you imagine that
this guy is
infinitely small then, really, the lengths
become the
same. We will also see another proof
of this formula, using changes of variables,
next week. But, I mean,
hopefully this is at least slightly convincing.
More questions? No.
OK. Let's see.
We have seen how to compute double integrals.
I have to tell you what they are good for
as well.
The definition we saw yesterday and the motivation
was in terms
of finding volumes, but that is not going
to be our
main preoccupation. Because finding volumes
is fun
but that is not all there is to life.
I mean, you are doing single integrals.
When you do single integrals it is usually
not to find the area
of some region of a plane. It is for something
else
usually. The way we actually think of
the double integral is really as summing the
values of a function
all around this region. We can use that to
get
information about maybe the region or about
the average
value of a function in that region and so
on.
Let's think about various uses of double integrals.
The first one that I will mention is actually
something
you thought maybe you could do with a single
integral,
but it is useful very often to do it as a
double integral.
It is to find the area of a given region r.
I give you some region in the plane and you
want to know just
its area. In various cases,
you could set this up as a single integral,
but often it could be useful to set it up
as a double integral.
How do you express the area as a double integral?
Well, the area of this region is the sum of
the areas of all
the little pieces. It means you want to sum
one dA
of the entire region. The area R is the double
integral over R of a function one.
One way to think about it, if you are really
still
attached to the idea of double integral as
a volume,
what this measures is the volume below the
graph of a
function one. The graph of a function one
is
just a horizontal plane at height one.
What you would be measuring is the volume
of a prism with base
r and height one. And the volume of that would
be, of course, base times height.
It would just be the area of r again.
But we don't actually need to think about
it that way.
Really, what we are doing is summing dA over
the entire
region. A related thing we can do,
imagine that, actually, this is some physical
object. I mean, it has to be a flat
object because we are just dealing with things
in the plane
so far. But you have a flat metal plate
or something and you would like to know its
mass.
Well, its mass is the sum of the masses of
every single
little piece. You would get that by
integrating the density. The density for a
flat object
would be the mass per unit area. So, you can
get the mass of a
flat object with density. Let's use delta
for density,
which is the mass per unit area.
Each little piece of your object will have
a mass,
which will be just the density, times its
area for each small
piece. And you will get the total mass
by summing these things. The mass will be
the double
integral of the density times the area element.
Now, if it has constant density,
if it is always the same material then,
of course, you could just take the density
out and you will get density times the total
area if you know
that it is always the same material.
But if, actually, it has varying density maybe
because it is some metallic thing with various
metals or
with varying thickness or something then you
can still get
the mass by integrating the density.
Of course, looking at flat objects might be
a little bit
strange. That is because we are only
doing double integrals so far. In a few weeks,
we will be triple integrals. And then we will
be able to do
solids in space, but one thing at
a time.
Another useful application is to find the
average value of
some quantity in a region. What does it mean
to take the
average value of some function f in this region
r?
Well, you know what the average of a finite
set of data is.
For example, if I asked you to compute your
average score on 18.02 problem sets,
you would just take the scores, add them and
divide by the
number of problem sets. What if there are
infinitely
many things? Say I ask you to find the
average temperature in this room.
Well, you would have to measure the temperature
everywhere.
And then add all of these together and divide
by the
number of data points. But, depending on how
careful
you are, actually, there are potentially
infinitely many points to look at.
The mathematical way to define the average
of a continuous set
of data is that you actually integrate the
function over the
entire set of data, and then you divide by
the size
of the sample, which is just the area of the
region. In fact, the average of f,
the notation we will use usually for that
is f with a bar
on top to tell us it is the average f.
We say we will take the integral of f and
we will divide
by the area of the region. You can really
think of it as
the sum of the values of f everywhere divided
by the number
of points everywhere. And so that is an average
where
everything is, actually, equally likely.
That is a uniform average where all the points
on the region,
all the little points of the region are equally
likely.
But maybe if want to do, say, an average of
some solid
with variable density or if you want to somehow
give more
importance to certain parts than to others
then you can actually
do a weighted average. What is a weighted
average?
Well, in the case of taking the
average your problem sets, if I tell you problem
set one
is worth twice as much as the others,
then you would count twice that score in the
sum and then you
would count it as two, of course, when you
divide.
The weighted average is the sum of the values,
but each weighted by a certain coefficient.
And then you will divide by the sum of the
weight.
It is a bit the same idea as when we replace
area by some
mass that tells you how important a given
piece.
We will actually have a density. Let's call
it delta again.
We will see what we divide by, but what we
will take is the
integral of a function times the density times
the area element.
Because this would correspond to the mass
element telling us
how to weight the various points of our region.
And then we would divide by the total weight,
which is the mass of a region, as defined
up there.
If a density is uniform then, of course, the
density gets out
and you can simplify and reduce to that if
all the points are
equally likely. Why is that important?
Well, that is important for various applications.
But one that you might have seen in physics,
we care about maybe where is the center of
mass of a given
object? The center of mass is basically
a point that you would say is right in the
middle of the
object. But, of course,
if the object has a very strange shape or
if somehow part
of it is heavier than the rest then that takes
a very different
meaning. Strictly speaking,
the center of mass of a solid is the point
where you would
have to concentrate all the mass if you wanted
it to behave
equivalently from a point of view of mechanics,
if you are trying to do translations of that
object.
If you are going to push that object that
would be really
where the equivalent point mass would lie.
The other way to think about it,
if I had a flat object then the center of
mass would basically
be the point where I would need to hold it
so it is perfectly
balanced. And, of course,
I cannot do this. Well, you get the idea.
And the center of mass of this eraser is somewhere
in the
middle. And so, in principle,
that is where I would have to put my finger
for it to stay.
Well, it doesn't work. But that is where the
center of
mass should be. I think it should be in the
middle. Maybe I shouldn't call this
three. I should call this 2a,
because it is really a special case of the
average value.
How do we find the center of mass of a flat
object with
density delta. If you have your object in
the
x, y plane then its center of mass
will be at positions that are actually just
the coordinates of
a center of mass, will just be weighted averages
of x and y on the solid. So, the center of
mass will be
a position that I will call x bar, y bar.
And these are really just the averages, the
average values of
x and of y in the solid. Just to give you
the formulas
again, x bar would be one over the mass times
the double
integral of x times density dA. And the same
thing with y.
y bar is the weighted average of a y coordinate
in your
region. You see, if you take a region
that is symmetric and has uniform density
that will just
give you the center of the region.
But if the region has a strange shape or if
a density is not
homogeneous, if parts of it are heavier then
you will get whatever the weighted average
will be.
And that will be the point where this thing
would be
balanced if you were trying to balance it
on a pole or on your
finger.
Any questions
so far? Yes.
No. Here I didn't set this up as a
iterated integral yet. The function that I
am
integrating is x times delta where density
will be given to
me maybe as a function of x and y.
And then I will integrate this dA.
And dA could mean dx over dy, it could mean
dy over dx,
it could be mean r dr d theta. I will choose
how to set it up
depending maybe on the shape of the region.
If my solid is actually just going to be round
then I might
want to use polar coordinates. If it is a
square,
I might want to use x, y coordinates.
If it is more complicated, well, I will choose
depending
on how I feel about it. Yes?
Delta is the density. In general, it is a
function of
x and y. If you imagine that your solid
is not homogenous then its density will depend
on which
piece of it you are looking at. Of course,
to compute this,
you need to know the density. If you have
a problem asking
you to find the center of mass of something
and you have no
information about the density, assume it is
uniform.
Take the density to be a constant.
Even take it to be a one. That is even easier.
I mean it is a general fact of math.
We don't care about units. If density is constant,
we might as well take it to be one.
That just means our mass unit becomes the
area unit.
Yes? That is a good question.
No, I don't think we could actually find the
center of mass
in polar coordinates by finding the average
of R or the average
of theta. For example,
take a disk center at the origin, well,
the center of mass should be at the origin.
But the average of R is certainly not zero
because R is
positive everywhere. So, that doesn't work.
You cannot get the polar coordinates of a
center of mass
just by taking the average of R and the average
of theta.
By the way, what is the average of theta?
If you take theta to from zero to 2pi, the
average theta will
be pi. If you take it to go from minus
pi to pi, the average theta will be zero.
So, there is a problem there. That actually
just doesn't
work, so we really have to compute x bar and
y bar.
But still we could set this up and then switch
to polar
coordinates to evaluate this integral.
But we still would be computing the average
values of x and y.
We are basically re-exploring mechanics and
motion of solids
here. The next thing is moment of
inertia. Just to remind you or in case
you somehow haven't seen it in physics yet,
the moment of inertia is basically to rotation
of a solid
where the mass is to translation.
In the following sense, the mass of a solid
is what
makes it hard to push it. How hard it is to
throw
something is related to its mass.
How hard it is to spin something, on the other
hand,
is given by its moment of inertia.
Maybe I should write this down. Mass is how
hard it is to
impart a translation motion to a solid.
I am using fancy words today. And the moment
of inertia --
The difference with a mass is that the moment
of inertia is
defined about some axis. You choose an axis.
Then you would try to measure how hard it
is to spin your
object around that axis. For example,
you can try to measure how hard it is to spin
this sheet of
paper about an axis that is in the center
of it.
We would try to spin it light that and see
how much effort I
would have to make. Well, for a sheet of paper
not
very much. That would measure the same
thing but it would be rotation motion about
that axis.
Maybe some of you know the definition but
I am going to try
to derive it again. I am sorry but it won't
be as
quite as detailed as the way you have probably
seen it in
physics, but I am not trying to replace your
physics teachers.
I am sure they are doing a great job.
What is the idea for the definition to find
a formula for
moment of inertia? The idea is to think about
kinetic energy. Kinetic energy is really when
you push something or when you try to make
it move and you have
to put some inertia to it. Then it has kinetic
energy.
And then, if you have the right device, you
can convert back
that kinetic energy into something else.
If you try to look at the kinetic energy of
a point mass,
so you have something with mass m going at
the velocity v,
well, that will be one-half of a mass times
the square of the
speed. I hope you have all seen that
formula some time before. Now, let's say instead
of just
trying to push this mass, I am going to make
it spin
around something. Instead of just somewhere,
maybe I will have the origin, and I am trying
to make it go
around the origin in a circle at a certain
angular velocity.
For a mass m at distance r, let's call r this
distance.
And angular velocity, let's call the angular
velocity
omega. I think that is what physicists
call it. Remember angular velocity is
just the rate of the change of the angle over
time.
It is d theta dt, if you want. Well, what
is the kinetic
energy now? Well, first we have to find out
what the speed is. What is the speed?
Well, if we are going on a circle of
radius r at angular velocity omega that means
that in unit
time we rotate by omega and we go by a distance
of r times
omega. The actual speed is the radius
times angular velocity. And so the kinetic
energy is
one-half mv squared, which is one-half m r
squared
omega squared. And so,
by similarity with that formula,
the coefficient of v squared is the mass,
and here we will say the coefficient of omega
squared,
so this thing is the moment of inertia.
That is how we define moment of inertia.
Now, that is only for a point mass.
And it is kind of fun to spin just a small
bowl,
but maybe you would like to spin actually
a larger solid and
try to define this moment of inertia.
Well, the moment inertia of a solid will be
just the sum of
the moments of inertia of all the little pieces.
What we will do is just cut our solid into
little chunks and
will sum this thing for each little piece.
For a solid with density delta, each little
piece has mass
which is the density times the amount of area.
This is equal actually. And the moment of
inertia of
that small portion of a solid will be delta
m,
the small mass, times r squared,
the square of a distance to the center of
the axis along which I
am spinning. That means if I sum these
things together, well, it has moment of inertia
delta m times r squared, which is r squared
times the
density times delta A. And so I will be summing
these
things together. And so, the moment of inertia
about the origin will be the double integral
of r squared
times density times dA.
The final formula for the moment of inertia
about the
origin is the double integral of a region
of r squared density
dA. If you are going to do it in x,
y coordinates, of course, r squared becomes
x
squared plus y squared, it is the square of
the
distance from the origin. When you integrate
this,
that tells you how hard it is to spin that
solid about the
origin. The motion that we try to do --
We keep this fixed and then we just rotate
around the origin.
Sorry. That is a pretty bad picture,
but hopefully you know what I mean.
And the name we use for that is I0.
And then the rotational kinetic energy
is one-half times this
moment of inertia times the square of the
angular velocity.
So that shows as that this replaces the mass
for rotation
motions. OK.
What about other kinds of rotations?
In particular, we have been rotating things
about just a point in the plane. What you
could imagine also is
instead you have your solid. What I have done
so far is I
have skewered it this way, and I am rotating
around the
axis. Instead, I could skewer it
through, say, the horizontal axis.
And then I could try to spin about the horizontal
axis so
then it would rotate in space in that direction
like that.
Let's say we do rotation about the x-axis.
Well, the idea would still be the same.
The moment of inertia for any small piece
of a solid would be
its mass element times the square of a distance
to the x
axes because that will be the radius of a
trajectory.
If you take this point here, it is going to
go in a circle
like that centered on the x-axis.
So the radius will just be this distance here.
Well, what is this distance? It is just y,
or maybe absolute value of y. Distance to
x-axis is absolute
value of y. What we actually care about is
the square of a distance, so it will just
be y squared.
The moment of inertia about the x-axis is
going to be obtained
by integrating y squared times the mass element.
It is slightly strange but I have y in inertia
about the
x-axis. But, if you think about it,
y tells me how far I am from the x-axis, so
how hard it will
be to spin around the x-axis. And I could
do the same about
any axis that I want. Just I would have to
sum the
square of a distance to the axis of rotation.
Maybe I should do an example. Yes?
Same thing as above, distance to the x-axis,
because that is what we care about.
For the moment of inertia, we want the square
of a
distance to the axis of rotation.
Let's do an example. Let's try to figure out
if we
have just a uniform disk how hard it is to
spin it around its
center. That shouldn't be very hard to
figure out. Say that we have a disk of
radius a
and we want to rotate it about its center.
And let's say that it is of uniform density.
And let's take just the density to be a one
so that we don't
really care about the density. What is the
moment of inertia
of that? Well, we have to integrate of
our disk r squared times the density, which
is one,
times dA. What is r squared?
You have here to resist the urge to say the
radius is just
a. We know the radius is a.
No, it is not a because we are looking at
rotation of any point
inside this disk. And, when you are inside
the
disk, the distance to the origin is not a.
It is less than a. It is actually anything
between
zero and a. Just to point out a pitfall,
r here is really a function on this disk.
And we are going to integrate this function.
Don't plug r equals a just yet. What coordinates
do we use to
compute this integral? They are probably polar
coordinates, unless you want a repeat of what
happened already
with x and y. That will tell us we want to
integrate r squared time r dr d theta.
And the bounds for r, well, r will go from
zero to a.
No matter which direction I go from the origin,
if I fixed it, r goes from zero to r equals
a.
The part of this ray that lives inside the
disk is always from
zero to a. And theta goes from,
well, zero to 2 pi for example. And now you
can compute this
integral. Well, I will let you figure it
out. But the inner integral becomes
a to the four over four and the outer multiplies
things by 2pi,
so you get pi a to the four over two.
OK. That is how hard it is to spin
this disk. Now, what about instead of
spinning it about the center we decided to
spin it about a point
on a second point. For example, think of a
Frisbee.
A Frisbee has this rim so you can actually
try to make it
rotate around the point on the circumference
by holding it near
the rim and spinning it there. How much harder
is that than
around the center? Well, we will try to compute
now the moment of inertia about this point.
We have two options. One is we keep the system
of
coordinates centers here. But then the formula
for
distance to this point becomes harder.
The other option, which is the one I will
choose,
is to change the coordinate so that this point
become the
origin. Let's do that.
About a point on the circumference,
what I would have to do maybe is set up my
region like that.
I have moved the origin so that it is on the
circumference of a
disk, and I will again try to find
the moment of inertia of this disk about the
origin.
It is still, for the the double integral of
r squared dA. But now I want to find out how
to set up the integral. I could try to use
x,
y coordinates and it would work.
Or I can use polar coordinates, and it works
a little bit
better that way. But both are doable.
Let's say I do it this way. I have to figure
out how to set
up my bounds. What are the bounds for r?
Well, if I fix a value for theta, which means
I chose an
angle here, now I am shooting a ray from the
origin in that
direction. I enter my region at r equals
zero. That hasn't changed.
The question is where do I exit the region?
What is that distance? Maybe you have seen
it in
recitation, maybe not. Let's see.
Actually, I should have written down the radius
of a circle is
a. So this distance here is 2a.
If you draw this segment in here, you know
that here you
have a right angle. You have a right triangle.
The hypotenuse here has length 2a.
This angle is theta. Well, this length is
2a cosine
theta. The polar coordinates equation
of this circle passing through the origin
is r equals 2a cosine
theta. So, r will go from zero to 2a
cosine theta. That is the distance here.
Now, what are the bounds for theta?
It is not quite zero to 2pi because, actually,
you see in this direction, if I shoot a ray
in this
direction I will never meet my region.
We have to actually think a bit more.
Well, the directions in which I will actually
hit my circle are
all the directions in the right half of a
plane.
I mean, of course, if I shoot very close to
the
axis, you might think, oh, I won't be in there.
But, actually, that is not true because here
the circle is tangent to the axis.
No matter which direction I take, I will still
have a little
tiny piece. The angle actually goes from
minus pi over two to pi over two.
If you compute that you will get,
well, the inner integral will be r to the
four over four
between zero and 2a cosine theta,
which will turn out to be 4a to the four cosine
to the four
theta. And now you will integrate that
for minus pi over two to pi over two.
And that is, again, the evil integral that
we had yesterday. Either we remember the method
from yesterday or we remember from yesterday
that actually
there are formulas in the notes to help you.
On homework, you can use these formulas.
In the notes at the beginning of section 3b
there are formulas
for these particular kinds of integrals.
And that will end up being three-halves of
pi a to the
four. In case you wanted to know,
it is three times harder to spin a Frisbee
about a point on
a circumference than around the center.
We got three times the moment of inertia about
the center.
OK. That is it.
Have a nice weekend.