Last time we saw things about gradients and
directional
derivatives. Before that we studied how to
look for minima and maxima of functions of
several variables.
And today we are going to look again at min/max
problems but in
a different setting, namely, one for variables
that
are not independent. And so what we will see
is you
may have heard of Lagrange multipliers.
And this is the one point in the term when
I can shine with
my French accent and say Lagrange's name properly.
OK. What are Lagrange multipliers
1:about? Well, the goal is to minimize
or maximize a function of several variables.
Let's say, for example, f of x, y, z,
but where these variables are no longer independent.
They are not independent. That means that
there is a
relation between them. The relation is maybe
some
equation of the form g of x, y, z equals some
constant.
You take the relation between x, y, z, you
call that g and
that gives you the constraint. And your goal
is to minimize f
only of those values of x, y, z that satisfy
the
constraint. What is one way to do that?
Well, one to do that, if the constraint is
very
simple, we can maybe solve for one of the
variables.
Maybe we can solve this equation for one of
the
variables, plug it back into f, and then we
have a usual
min/max problem that we have seen how to do.
The problem is sometimes you cannot actually
solve for x,
y, z in here because this condition is too
complicated and
then we need a new method. That is what we
are going to do.
Why would we care about that? Well, one example
is actually
in physics. Maybe you have seen in
thermodynamics that you study quantities about
gases,
and those quantities that involve pressure,
volume and temperature. And pressure,
volume and temperature are not independent
of each other.
I mean you know probably the equation PV = NRT.
And, of course, there you could actually solve
to express things in terms of one or the other.
But sometimes it is more convenient to keep
all three
variables but treat them as constrained.
It is just an example of a situation where
you might want
to do this. Anyway, we will look mostly at
particular examples, but just to point out
that this
is useful when you study guesses in physics.
The first observation is we cannot use our
usual method of
looking for critical points of f.
Because critical points of f typically will
not satisfy this
condition and so won't be good solutions.
We need something else. Let's look at an example,
and we will see how that leads us to the method.
For example, let's say that I want to find
the point closest to the origin -- --
on the hyperbola xy equals
3 in the plane. That means I have this
hyperbola, and I am asking myself what is
the point on it
that is the closest to the origin?
I mean we can solve this by elementary geometry,
we don't need actually Lagrange multipliers,
but we are going to do it with Lagrange multipliers
because it
is a pretty good example. What does it mean?
Well, it means that we want to minimize distance
to the origin.
What is the distance to the origin?
If I have a point, at coordinates (x,
y) and then the distance to the origin is
square root of x
squared plus y squared. Well, do we really
want to
minimize that or can we minimize something
easier?
Yeah. Maybe we can minimize the
square of a distance. Let's forget this guy
and
instead -- Actually, we will minimize f of
x,
y equals x squared plus y squared,
that looks better, subject to the constraint
xy =
3. And so we will call this thing
g of x, y to illustrate the general method.
Let's look at a picture. Here you can see
in yellow the
hyperbola xy equals three. And we are going
to look for
the points that are the closest to the origin.
What can we do? Well, for example,
6:we can plot the function x squared plus
y squared,
function f. That is the contour plot of f
with a hyperbola on top of it. Now let's see
what we can do
with that. Well, let's ask ourselves,
for example, if I look at points where f
equals 20 now. I think I am at 20 but you
cannot really see it. That is a circle with
a point
whose distant square is 20. Well, can I find
a solution if
I am on the hyperbola? Yes, there are four
points at
this distance. Can I do better?
Well, let's decrease for distance.
Yes, we can still find points on the hyperbola
and so on.
Except if we go too low then there are no
points on this
circle anymore in the hyperbola. If we decrease
the value of f
that we want to look at that will somehow
limit value beyond
which we cannot go, and that is the minimum
of f.
We are trying to look for the smallest value
of f that will
actually be realized on the hyperbola.
When does that happen? Well, I have to backtrack
a
little bit. It seems like the limiting case
is basically here. It is when the circle is
tangent to the hyperbola. That is the smallest
circle
that will hit the hyperbola. If I take a larger
value of f,
I will have solutions. If I take a smaller
I will not have any solutions anymore.
So, that is the situation that we want to
solve for.
How do we find that minimum? Well, a key observation
that is
valid on this picture, and that actually remain
true
in the completely general case, is that when
we have a minimum
the level curve of f is actually tangent to
our hyperbola.
It is tangent to the set of points where x,
y equals three, to the hyperbola.
Let's write that down. We observe that at
the minimum
the level curve of f is tangent to the hyperbola.
Remember, the hyperbola is given by the equal
g equals
three, so it is a level curve of g.
We have a level curve of f and a level curve
of g that are
tangent to each other. And I claim that is
going to be
the general situation that we are interested
in.
How do we try to solve for points where this
happens?
How do we find x, y where the level curves
of f
and g are tangent to each other? Let's think
for a second.
If the two level curves are tangent to each
other that means
they have the same tangent line. That means
that the normal
vectors should be parallel. Let me maybe draw
a picture
here. This is the level curve maybe f
equals something. And this is the level curve
g
equals constant. Here my constant is three.
Well, if I look for gradient vectors, the
gradient of f will
be perpendicular to the level curve of f.
The gradient of g will be perpendicular to
the level curve
of g. They don't have any reason to
be of the same size, but they have to be parallel
to
each other. Of course, they could also be
parallel pointing in opposite directions.
But the key point is that when this happens
the gradient of f
is parallel to the gradient of g.
Well, let's check that. Here is a point.
And I can plot the gradient of f in blue.
The gradient of g in yellow. And you see,
11:in most of these places, somehow the two
gradients are
not really parallel. Actually, I should not
be
looking at random points. I should be looking
only on the
hyperbola. I want points on the hyperbola
where the two gradients are parallel.
Well, when does that happen? Well, it looks
like it will
happen here. When I am at a minimum,
the two gradient vectors are parallel.
It is not really proof. It is an example that
seems to
be convincing. So far things work pretty well.
How do we decide if two vectors are parallel?
Well, they are parallel when they are proportional
to each
other. You can write one of them as a
constant times the other one, and that constant
usually one
uses the Greek letter lambda. I don't know
if you have seen
it before. It is the Greek letter for L.
And probably, I am sure, it is somebody's
idea of paying tribute to Lagrange by putting
an L in
there. Lambda is just a constant.
And we are looking for a scalar lambda and
points x and y where
this holds. In fact,
what we are doing is replacing min/max problems
in two
variables with a constraint between them by
a set of
equations involving, you will see, three variables.
We had min/max with two variables x, y,
but no independent. We had a constraint g
of x,
y equals constant. And that becomes something
new.
That becomes a system of equations
where we have to
solve, well, let's write down what it means
for gradient f to
be proportional to gradient g. That means
that f sub x should
be lambda times g sub x, and f sub y should
be lambda
times g sub y. Because the gradient vectors
here are f sub x, f sub y and g sub x,
g sub y. If you have a third variable z
then you have also an equation f sub z equals
lambda g sub z.
Now, let's see. How many unknowns do we have
in
these equations? Well, there is x,
there is y and there is lambda. We have three
unknowns and have
only two equations. Something is missing.
Well, I mean x and y are not actually independent.
They are related by the equation g of x,
y equals c, so we need to add the constraint
g equals c.
And now we have three equations involving
three variables.
Let's see how that works. Here remember we
have f equals
x squared y squared and g = xy. What is f
sub x?
It is going to be 2x equals lambda times,
what is g sub x, y.
Maybe I should write here f sub x equals lambda
g sub x just to
remind you. Then we have f sub y equals
lambda g sub y. F sub y is 2y equals lambda
times g sub y is x. And then our third equation
g
equals c becomes xy equals three.
So, that is what you would have to solve.
Any questions at this point? No.
Yes? How do I know the direction of
a gradient? Do you mean how do I know that
it is perpendicular to a level curve?
Oh, how do I know if it points in that direction
on the
opposite one? Well, that depends.
I mean we'd seen in last time, but the gradient
is
perpendicular to the level and points towards
higher values of
a function. So it could be -- Wait.
What did I have? It could be that my gradient
16:vectors up there actually point in opposite
directions.
It doesn't matter to me because it will still
look the same in
terms of the equation, just lambda will be
positive or
negative, depending on the case. I can handle
both situations.
It's not a problem. I can allow lambda to
be
positive or negative. Well, in this example,
it looks like lambda will be positive.
If you look at the picture on the plot.
Yes? Well, because actually they are
not equal to each other. If you look at this
point where
the hyperbola and the circle touch each other,
first of all, I don't know which circle I
am
going to look at. I am trying to solve,
actually, for the radius of the circle.
I am trying to find what the minimum value
of f is.
And, second, at that point,
the value of f and the value of g are not
equal.
g is equal to three because I want the hyperbola
x equals
three. The value of f will be the
square of a distance, whatever that is.
I think it will end up being 6, but we will
see.
So, you cannot really set them equal because
you don't know
what f is equal to in advance. Yes?
Not quite. Actually, here I am just using
this idea of finding a point closest to the
origin to
illustrate an example of a min/max problem.
The general problem we are trying to solve
is minimize f
subject to g equals constant. And what we
are going to do for
that is we are really going to say instead
let's look at places
where gradient f and gradient g are parallel
to each other and
solve for equations of that. I think we completely
lose the
notion of closest point if we just look at
these equations.
We don't really say anything about closest
points anymore.
Of course, that is what they mean in the end.
But, in the general setting, there is no closest
point
involved anymore. OK.
Yes? Yes.
It is always going to be the case that,
at the minimum, or at the maximum of a function
subject to a constraint, the level curves
of f and the
level curves of g will be tangent to each
other.
That is the basis for this method.
I am going to justify that soon. It could
be minimum or maximum.
In three-dimensions it could even be a saddle
point.
And, in fact, I should say in advance,
this method will not tell us whether it is
a minimum or a
maximum. We do not have any way of
19:knowing, except for testing values.
We cannot use second derivative tests or anything
like that.
I will get back to that. Yes?
Yes. Here you can set y equals to
favor x. Then you can minimize x squared
plus nine over x squared. In general, if I
am trying to
solve a more complicated problem, I might
not be able to
solve. I am doing an example where,
indeed, here you could solve and remove one
variable,
but you cannot always do that. And this method
will still work.
The other one won't. OK.
I don't see any other questions. Are there
any other questions?
No. OK.
I see a lot of students stretching and so
on,
so it is very confusing for me. How do we
solve these equations?
20:Well, the answer is in general we might
be in deep trouble.
There is no general method for solving the
equations that you
get from this method. You just have to think
about
them. Sometimes it will be very easy.
Sometimes it will be so hard that you cannot
actually do it
without the computer. Sometimes it will be
just hard
enough to be on Part B of this week's problem
set.
I claim in this case we can actually do it
without so much
trouble, because actually we can think of
this as a two by two
linear system in x and y. Well, let me do
something.
Let me rewrite the first two equations as
2x - lambda y = 0.
And lambda x - 2y = 0. And xy = 3.
That is what we want to solve. Well, I can
put this into
matrix form. Two minus lambda,
lambda minus two times x, y equals 0,0.
Now, how do I solve a linear system matrix
times x,
y equals zero? Well, I always have an obvious
solution. X and y both equal to zero.
Is that a good solution? No, because zero
times zero is
not three. We want another solution,
the trivial solution. 0,0 does not solve the
constraint equation xy equals three, so we
want another
solution. When do we have another
solution? Well, when the determinant of a
matrix is zero. We have other solutions that
exist only if determinant of a matrix is zero.
M is this guy. Let's compute the determinant.
Well, that seems to be negative four plus
lambda squared.
23:That is zero exactly when lambda squared
equals four,
which is lambda is plus or minus two.
Already you see here it is a the level of
difficulty that is
a little bit much for an exam but perfectly
fine for a problem
set or for a beautiful lecture like this one.
How do we deal with -- Well, we have two cases
to look at.
Lambda equals two or lambda equals minus two.
Let's start with lambda equals two.
If I set lambda equals two, what does this
equation become?
Well, it becomes x equals y. This one becomes
y equals x.
Well, they seem to be the same. x equals y.
And then the equation xy equals three becomes,
well, x squared equals three. I have two solutions.
One is x equals root three and, therefore,
y equals root three
as well, or negative root three and negative
root three.
Let's look at the other case. If I set lambda
equal to
negative two then I get 2x equals negative
2y.
That means x equals negative y. The second
one,
2y equals negative 2x. That is y equals negative
x.
Well, that is the same thing. And xy equals
three becomes
negative x squared equals three. Can we solve
that?
No. There are no solutions here.
Now we have two candidate points which are
these two
points, root three, root three or negative
root
three, negative root three. OK.
Let's actually look at what we have here.
Maybe you cannot read the coordinates, but
the point that
I have here is indeed root three, root three.
How do we see that lambda equals two?
Well, if you look at this picture, the gradient
of f,
that is the blue vector, is indeed twice the
yellow
vector, gradient g. That is where you read
the
value of lambda. And we have the other solution
which is somewhere here. Negative root three,
negative root there. And there, again,
lambda equals two. The two vectors are
proportional by a factor of two. Yes?
No, solutions are not quite guaranteed to
be absolute minima
or maxima. They are guaranteed to be
somehow critical points end of a constraint.
That means if you were able to solve and eliminate
the variable
that would be a critical point. When you have
the same problem,
as we have critical points, are they maxima
or minima?
And the answer is, well, we won't know until
we
check. More questions?
No. Yes?
What is a Lagrange multiplier? Well, it is
this number lambda
that is called the multiplier here.
It is a multiplier because it is what you
have to multiply
gradient of g by to get gradient of f.
It multiplies.
Let's try to see why is this method valid?
Because so far I have shown you pictures and
have said see they
are tangent. But why is it that they have
to
be tangent in general? Let's think about it.
Let's say that we are at constrained min or
max.
What that means is that if I move on the level
g equals
constant then the value of f should only increase
or only
decrease. But it means,
in particular, to first order it will not
change. At an unconstrained min or max,
partial derivatives are zero. In this case,
derivatives are zero only in the allowed directions.
And the allowed directions are those that
stay on the levels of
this g equals constant. In any direction along
the
level set g = c the rate of change of f must
be zero.
That is what happens at minima or maxima.
Except here, of course, we look only at the
allowed directions. Let's say the same thing
in
terms of directional derivatives.
That means for any direction that is tangent
to the
constraint level g equal c, we must have df
over ds in the
direction of u equals zero. I will draw a
picture.
Let's say now I am in three variables just
to give you
different examples. Here I have a level surface
g
equals c. I am at my point.
And if I move in any direction that is on
the level surface,
so I move in the direction u tangent to the
level surface,
then the rate of change of f in that direction
should be zero.
Now, remember what the formula is for this
guy.
Well, we have seen that this guy is actually
radiant f dot u.
That means any such vector u must be perpendicular
to the
gradient of f. That means that the gradient
of
f should be perpendicular to anything that
is tangent to this
level. That means the gradient of f
should be perpendicular to the level set.
That is what we have shown.
But we know another vector that is also perpendicular
to the
level set of g. That is the gradient of g.
We conclude that the gradient of f must be
parallel to the
gradient of g because both are perpendicular
to the level set
of g. I see confused faces,
so let me try to tell you again where that
comes from.
We said if we had a constrained minimum or
maximum,
if we move in the level set of g, f doesn't
change.
Well, it doesn't change to first order.
It is the same idea as when you are looking
for a minimum you
set the derivative equal to zero.
So the derivative in any direction, tangent
to g equals
c, should be the directional derivative of
f,
in any such direction, should be zero.
That is what we mean by critical point of
f.
And so that means that any vector u, any unit
vector
tangent to the level set of g is going to
be perpendicular to the
gradient of f. That means that the gradient
of
f is perpendicular to the level set of g.
If you want, that means the level sets of
f
and g are tangent to each other. That is justifying
what we have
observed in the picture that the two level
sets have to be
tangent to each other at the prime minimum
or maximum.
Does that make a little bit of sense?
Kind of. I see at least a few faces
nodding so I take that to be a positive answer.
Since I have been asked by several of you,
how do I know if it is a maximum or a minimum?
Well, warning, the method doesn't tell whether
a solution
is a minimum or a maximum.
How do we do it? Well, more bad news.
We cannot use the second derivative test.
And the reason for that is that we care actually
only about
these specific directions that are tangent
to variable of g.
And we don't want to bother to try to define
directional second
derivatives. Not to mention that actually
it
wouldn't work. There is a criterion but it
is
much more complicated than that. Basically,
the answer for us is
that we don't have a second derivative test
in this
situation. What are we left with?
Well, we are just left with comparing values.
Say that in this problem you found a point
where f equals
three, a point where f equals nine, a point
where f equals 15.
Well, then probably the minimum is the point
where f equals
35:three and the maximum is 15. Actually,
in this case,
where we found minima, these two points are
tied for
minimum. What about the maximum?
What is the maximum of f on the hyperbola?
Well, it is infinity because the point can
go as far as you
want from the origin. But the general idea
is if we
have a good reason to believe that there should
be a minimum,
and it's not like at infinity or something
weird like that,
then the minimum will be a solution of the
Lagrange
multiplier equations. We just look for all
the
solutions and then we choose the one that
gives us the lowest
value. Is that good enough?
Let me actually write that down.
To find the minimum or the maximum, we compare
values of f
at the various solutions -- --
to Lagrange multiplier
equations.
37:I should say also that sometimes you can
just conclude
by thinking geometrically. In this case,
when it is asking you which point is closest
to the origin
you can just see that your answer is the correct
one.
Let's do an advanced example. Advanced means
that -- Well,
this one I didn't actually dare to put on
top of the other
problem sets. Instead, I am going to do it.
What is this going to be about? We are going
to look for a
surface minimizing pyramid. Let's say that
we want to build
a pyramid with a given triangular base -- -- and
a
given volume. Say that I have maybe in the
x,
y plane I am giving you some triangle.
And I am going to try to build a pyramid.
Of course, I can choose where to put the top
of a pyramid.
This guy will end up being behind now.
And the constraint and the goal is to minimize
the total surface
area. The first time I taught this
class, it was a few years ago, was just before
they built the
Stata Center. And then I used to motivate
this problem by saying Frank Gehry has gone
crazy and has
been given a triangular plot of land he wants
to put a pyramid.
There needs to be the right amount of volume
so that you can
put all the offices in there. And he wants
it to be,
actually, covered in solid gold.
And because that is expensive, the administration
wants him to
cut the costs a bit. And so you have to minimize
the
total size so that it doesn't cost too much.
We will see if MIT comes up with a triangular
pyramid
building. Hopefully not.
It could be our next dorm, you never know.
Anyway, it is a fine geometry problem.
Let's try to think about how we can do this.
The natural way to think about it would be
-- Well,
what do we have to look for first?
We have to look for the position of that top
point.
Remember we know that the volume of a pyramid
is one-third
the area of base times height. In fact, fixing
the volume,
knowing that we have fixed the area of a base,
means that we are fixing the height of the
pyramid.
The height is completely fixed. What we have
to choose just is
where do we put that top point? Do we put
it smack in the
middle of a triangle or to a side or even
anywhere we want?
Its z coordinate is fixed. Let's call h the
height.
What we could do is something like this.
We say we have three points of a base.
Let's call them p1 at (x1, y1,0); p2 at (x2,
y2,0); p3 at (x3, y3,0).
This point p is the unknown point at (x, y,
h). We know the height.
And then we want to minimize the sum of the
areas of these
three triangles. One here, one here and one
at
the back. And areas of triangles we know
how to express by using length of cross-product.
It becomes a function of x and y.
And you can try to minimize it. Actually,
it doesn't quite work.
The formulas are just too complicated.
You will never get there. What happens is
actually maybe
we need better coordinates. Why do we need
better
coordinates? That is because the geometry
is
kind of difficult to do if you use x, y coordinates.
I mean formula for cross-product is fine,
but then the length of the vector will be
annoying and just
doesn't look good. Instead, let's think about
it
differently.
I claim if we do it this way and we express
the area as a
function of x, y, well, actually we can't
solve for a minimum. Here is another way to
do it.
Well, what has worked pretty well for us so
far is this
geometric idea of base times height.
So let's think in terms of the heights of
side triangles.
I am going to use the height of these things.
And I am going to say that the area will be
the sum of three
terms, which are three bases times three heights.
Let's give names to these quantities.
Actually, for that it is going to be good
to have the point in
the xy plane that lives directly below p.
Let's call it q. P is the point that coordinates
44:x, y, h. And let's call q the point that
is just below it and so it' coordinates are
x,
y, 0. Let's see.
Let me draw a map of this thing. p1, p2, p3
and I have my point
q in the middle. Let's see.
To know these areas, I need to know the base.
Well, the base I can decide that I know it
because it is
part of my given data. I know the sides of
this
triangle. Let me call the lengths a1,
a2, a3. I also need to know the height,
so I need to know these lengths.
How do I know these lengths? Well, its distance
in space,
but it is a little bit annoying.
But maybe I can reduce it to a distance in
the plane by looking
instead at this distance here. Let me give
names to the
distances from q to the sides. Let's call
u1,
u2, u3 the distances from q to the sides.
Well, now I can claim I can find, actually,
sorry. I need to draw one more thing.
I claim I have a nice formula for the area,
because this is vertical and this is horizontal
so this
length here is u3, this length here is h.
So what is this length here? It is the square
root of u3
squared plus h squared. And similarly for
these other
guys. They are square roots of a u
squared plus h squared. The heights of the
faces are
square root of u1 squared times h squared.
And similarly with u2 and u3. So the total
side area is going
to be the area of the first faces,
one-half of base times height, plus one-half
of a base times a
height plus one-half of the third one.
It doesn't look so much better. But, trust
me,
it will get better. Now, that is a function
of
three variables, u1, u2, u3.
And how do we relate u1, u2, u3 to each other?
They are probably not independent.
Well, let's cut this triangle here into three
pieces like
that. Then each piece has side --
Well, let's look at it the piece of the bottom.
It has base a3, height u3. Cutting base into
three tells
you that the area of a base is one-half of
a1,
u1 plus one-half of a2, u2 plus one-half of
a3,
u3. And that is our constraint.
My three variables, u1, u2, u3, are constrained
in
this way. The sum of this figure must be
the area of a base. And I want to minimize
that guy.
So that is my g and that guy here is my f.
Now we try to apply our Lagrange multiplier
equations.
Well, partial f of a partial u1 is -- Well,
if you do the calculation, you will see it
is one-half a1,
u1 over square root of u1^2 plus h^2 equals
lambda,
what is partial g, partial a1?
That one you can do, I am sure. It is one-half
a1.
Oh, these guys simplify. If you do the same
with the
second one -- --
things simplify again.
And the same with the third one. Well, you
will get,
after simplifying, u3 over square root of
u3
squared plus h squared equals lambda.
Now, that means this guy equals this guy equals
this guy.
They are all equal to lambda. And, if you
think about it,
that means that u1 = u2 = u3. See, it looked
like scary
equations but the solution is very simple.
What does it mean? It means that our point
q
should be equidistant from all three sides.
That is called the incenter. Q should be in
the incenter.
The next time you have to build a golden pyramid
and don't want
to go broke, well, you know where to put the
top.
If that was a bit fast, sorry. Anyway, it
is not completely
crucial. But go over it and you will see
it works. Have a nice weekend.
50: