The following content is provided under a
Creative
Commons license. Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer high quality
educational
resources for free. To make a donation or
to view
additional materials from hundreds of MIT
courses,
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at ocw.mit.edu.
So far we have learned about partial derivatives
and how to
use them to find minima and maxima of functions
of two
variables or several variables. And now we
are going to try to
study, in more detail, how functions of several
variables behave, how to compete their
variations. How to estimate the variation
in arbitrary directions. And so for that we
are going to
need some more tools actually to study this
things.
More tools to study functions.
Today's topic is going to be differentials.
And, just to motivate that, let me remind
you about one
trick that you probably know from single variable
calculus,
namely implicit differentiation.
Let's say that you have a function y equals
f of x then
you would sometimes write dy equals f prime
of x times dx.
And then maybe you would --
We use implicit differentiation to
actually relate infinitesimal changes in y
with infinitesimal
changes in x. And one thing we can do with
that, for example, is actually figure out
the rate
of change dy by dx, but also the reciprocal
dx by
dy. And so, for example,
let's say that we have y equals inverse sin(x).
Then we can write x equals sin(y).
And, from there, we can actually find out
what
is the derivative of this function if we didn't
know the
answer already by writing dx equals cosine
y dy.
That tells us that dy over dx is going to
be one over cosine
y. And now cosine for relation to
sine is basically one over square root of
one minus x^2.
And that is how you find the formula for the
derivative of
the inverse sine function. A formula that
you probably
already knew, but that is one way to derive
it. Now we are going to use also
these kinds of notations, dx, dy and so on,
but use them for functions of several variables.
And, of course, we will have to learn what
the
rules of manipulation are and what we can
do with them.
The actual name of that is the total differential,
as opposed to the partial derivatives.
The total differential includes all of the
various causes that
can change -- Sorry. All the contributions
that can
cause the value of your function f to change.
Namely, let's say that you have a function
maybe of three
variables, x, y, z,
then you would write df equals f sub x dx
plus f sub y dy plus
f sub z dz. Maybe, just to remind you of
the other notation, partial f over partial
x dx
plus partial f over partial y dy plus partial
f over partial z
dz. Now, what is this object?
What are the things on either side of this
equality?
Well, they are called differentials.
And they are not numbers, they are not vectors,
they are not matrices, they are a different
kind of
object. These things have their own
rules of manipulations, and we have to learn
what we
can do with them. So how do we think about
them?
First of all, how do we not think about them?
Here is an important thing to know.
Important. df is not the same thing as
delta f. That is meant to be a number.
It is going to be a number once you have a
small variation of x,
a small variation of y, a small variation
of z.
These are numbers. Delta x, delta y and delta
z
are actual numbers, and this becomes a number.
This guy actually is not a number.
You cannot give it a particular value.
All you can do with a differential is express
it in
terms of other differentials. In fact, this
dx,
dy and dz, well, they are mostly symbols out
there. But if you want to think about
them, they are the differentials of x, y and
z.
In fact, you can think of these differentials
as placeholders
where you will put other things. Of course,
they represent,
you know, there is this idea of changes in
x,
y, z and f. One way that one could explain
it, and I don't really like it, is to say
they represent
infinitesimal changes. Another way to say
it,
and I think that is probably closer to the
truth,
is that these things are somehow placeholders
to put
values and get a tangent approximation.
For example, if I do replace these symbols
by delta x, delta y and delta z numbers then
I will actually get
a numerical quantity. And that will be an
approximation formula for delta. It will be
the linear
approximation, a tangent plane approximation.
What we can do -- Well, let me start first
with maybe
something even before that. The first thing
that it does is
it can encode how changes in x, y, z affect
the value of f.
I would say that is the most general answer
to what is this
formula, what are these differentials.
It is a relation between x, y, z and f.
And this is a placeholder for small variations,
delta x, delta y and delta z to get an approximation
formula.
Which is delta f is approximately equal to
fx delta
x fy delta y fz delta z. It is getting cramped,
but I am sure you know what is going on here.
And observe how this one is actually equal
while that one is
approximately equal. So they are really not
the same.
Another thing that the notation suggests we
can do,
and they claim we can do, is divide everything
by some
variable that everybody depends on.
Say, for example, that x, y and z actually
depend
on some parameter t then they will vary, at
a certain rate,
dx over dt, dy over dt, dz over dt.
And what the differential will tell us then
is the rate of
change of f as a function of t, when you plug
in these values
of x, y, z, you will get df over dt by
dividing everything by dt in here.
The first thing we can do is divide by something
like dt to
get infinitesimal rate of change.
Well, let me just say rate of change.
df over dt equals f sub x dx over dt plus
f sub y dy over dt
plus f sub z dz over dt. And that corresponds
to the
situation where x is a function of t, y is
a function of t and z
is a function of t. That means you can plug
in
these values into f to get, well, the value
of f will
depend on t, and then you can find the rate
of change with t of a value of f.
These are the basic rules. And this is known
as the chain
rule. It is one instance of a chain
rule, which tells you when you have a
function that depends on something,
and that something in turn depends on something
else,
how to find the rate of change of a function
on the new
variable in terms of the derivatives of a
function and
also the dependence between the various variables.
Any questions so far? No.
OK. A word of warming,
in particular, about what I said up here.
It is kind of unfortunate, but the textbook
actually has a
serious mistake on that. I mean they do have
a couple of
formulas where they mix a d with a delta,
and I warn you not to
do that, please. I mean there are d's and
there
are delta's, and basically they don't live
in the same world.
They don't see each other. The textbook is
lying to you.
Let's see. The first and the second
claims, I don't really need to justify
because the first one is just stating some
general principle,
but I am not making a precise mathematical
claim.
The second one, well, we know the approximation
formula already, so I don't need to justify
it
for you. But, on the other hand,
this formula here, I mean, you probably have
a
right to expect some reason for why this works.
Why is this valid? After all, I first told
you we
have these new mysterious objects.
And then I am telling you we can do that,
but I kind of
pulled it out of my hat. I mean I don't have
a hat.
Why is this valid? How can I get to this?
Here is a first attempt of justifying how
to get there.
Let's see. Well, we said df is f sub x dx
plus f sub y dy plus f sub z dz. But we know
if x is a function
of t then dx is x prime of t dt, dy is y prime
of t dt,
dz is z prime of t dt. If we plug these into
that
formula, we will get that df is f sub x times
x prime t dt plus
f sub y y prime of t dt plus f sub z z prime
of t dt.
And now I have a relation between df and dt.
See, I got df equals sometimes times dt.
That means the rate of change of f with respect
to t should be
that coefficient. If I divide by dt then I
get
the chain rule. That kind of works,
but that shouldn't be completely satisfactory.
Let's say that you are a true skeptic and
you don't believe in
differentials yet then it is maybe not very
good that I
actually used more of these differential notations
in
deriving the answer. That is actually not
how it is
proved. The way in which you prove the
chain rule is not this way because we shouldn't
have too
much trust in differentials just yet.
I mean at the end of today's lecture, yes,
probably we should believe in them,
but so far we should be a little bit reluctant
to believe
these kind of strange objects telling us weird
things.
Here is a better way to think about it.
One thing that we have trust in so far are
approximation
formulas. We should have trust in them.
We should believe that if we change x a little
bit,
if we change y a little bit then we are actually
going to
get a change in f that is approximately given
by these
guys. And this is true for any
changes in x, y, z,
but in particular let's look at the changes
that we get if we
just take these formulas as function of time
and change time
a little bit by delta t. We will actually
use the
changes in x, y, z in a small time delta t.
Let's divide everybody by delta t.
Here I am just dividing numbers so I am not
actually playing any
tricks on you. I mean we don't really know
what it means to divide differentials,
but dividing numbers is something we know.
And now, if I take delta t very small, this
guy tends to the
derivative, df over dt. Remember, the definition
of df
over dt is the limit of this ratio when the
time interval
delta t tends to zero. That means if I choose
smaller
and smaller values of delta t then these ratios
of numbers
will actually tend to some value,
and that value is the derivative.
Similarly, here delta x over delta t, when
delta t is really
small, will tend to the derivative dx/dt.
And similarly for the others.
That means, in particular, we take the limit
as delta t
tends to zero and we get df over dt on one
side and on the other
side we get f sub x dx over dt plus f sub
y dy over dt plus f
sub z dz over dt. And the approximation becomes
better and better. Remember when we write
approximately equal that means it is not quite
the same,
but if we take smaller variations then actually
we will
end up with values that are closer and closer.
When we take the limit, as delta t tends to
zero,
eventually we get an equality.
I mean mathematicians have more complicated
words to justify
this statement. I will spare them for now,
and you will see them when you take analysis
if you go in that
direction. Any questions so far?
No. OK.
Let's check this with an example.
Let's say that we really don't have any faith
in these things
so let's try to do it. Let's say I give you
a function
that is x ^2 y z. And let's say that maybe
x will
be t, y will be e^t and z will be sin(t).
What does the chain rule say? Well, the chain
rule tells us
that dw/dt is, we start with partial w over
partial x, well, what is that?
That is 2xy, and maybe I should point out
that this is w sub x, times dx over dt plus
-- Well,
w sub y is x squared times dy over dt plus
w sub z,
which is going to be just one, dz over dt.
And so now let's plug in the actual values
of these things.
x is t and y is e^t, so that will be 2t e
to the t,
dx over dt is one plus x squared is t squared,
dy over dt is e over t, plus dz over dt is
cosine t.
At the end of calculation we get 2t e to the
t plus t squared
e to the t plus cosine t. That is what the
chain rule
tells us. How else could we find that?
Well, we could just plug in values of x, y
and z,
x plus w is a function of t, and take its
derivative.
Let's do that just for verification.
It should be exactly the same answer.
And, in fact, in this case,
the two calculations are roughly equal in
complication.
But say that your function of x, y, z was
much more
complicated than that, or maybe you actually
didn't
know a formula for it, you only knew its partial
derivatives, then you would need to use the
chain rule. So, sometimes plugging in
values is easier but not always.
Let's just check quickly. The other method
would be to
substitute. W as a function of t.
Remember w was x^2y z. x was t, so you get
t squared,
y is e to the t, plus z was sine t.
dw over dt, we know how to take the derivative
using single
variable calculus. Well, we should know.
If we don't know then we should take a look
at 18.01 again.
The product rule that will be derivative of
t squared is 2t
times e to the t plus t squared time the derivative
of e to the
t is e to the t plus cosine t. And that is
the same answer as
over there. I ended up writing,
you know, maybe I wrote slightly more here,
but actually the amount of calculations really
was pretty
much the same. Any questions about that?
Yes? What kind of object is w?
Well, you can think of w as just another variable
that is
given as a function of x, y and z, for example.
You would have a function of x, y, z defined
by this formula,
and I call it w. I call its value w so that
I
can substitute t instead of x, y, z.
Well, let's think of w as a function of three
variables.
And then, when I plug in the dependents of
these three
variables on t, then it becomes just a function
of t. I mean, really,
my w here is pretty much what I called f before.
There is no major difference between the two.
Any other questions? No.
OK. Let's see.
Here is an application of what we have seen.
Let's say that you want to understand actually
all these
rules about taking derivatives in single variable
calculus.
What I showed you at the beginning, and then
erased,
basically justifies how to take the derivative
of a reciprocal
function. And for that you didn't need
multivariable calculus. But let's try to justify
the
product rule, for example,
for the derivative. An application of this
actually
is to justify the product and quotient rules.
Let's think, for example,
of a function of two variables, u and v, that
is just the
product uv. And let's say that u and v are
actually functions of one variable t.
Then, well, d of uv over dt is given by the
chain rule applied
to f. This is df over dt.
So df over dt should be f sub q du over dt
plus f sub v plus dv
over dt. But now what is the partial of
f with respect to u? It is v.
That is v du over dt. And partial of f with
respect
to v is going to be just u, dv over dt.
So you get back the usual product rule.
That is a slightly complicated way of deriving
it,
but that is a valid way of understanding how
to take the
derivative of a product by thinking of the
product first as
a function of variables, which are u and v.
And then say, oh, but u and v were actually
functions of a variable t. And then you do
the
differentiation in two stages using the chain
rule.
Similarly, you can do the quotient rule just
for practice.
If I give you the function g equals u of v.
Right now I am thinking of it as a function
of two variables,
u and v. U and v themselves are actually
going to be functions of t. Then, well, dg
over dt is going
to be partial g, partial u.
How much is that? How much is partial g,
partial u? One over v times du over dt
plus -- Well, next we need to have partial
g
over partial v. Well, what is the derivative
of
this with respect to v? Here we need to know
how to
differentiate the inverse. It is minus u over
v squared
times dv over dt. And that is actually the
usual
quotient rule just written in a slightly different
way.
I mean, just in case you really want to see
it,
if you clear denominators for v squared then
you will see
basically u prime times v minus v prime times
u.
Now let's go to something even more crazy.
I claim we can do chain rules with more variables.
Let's say that I have a quantity.
Let's call it w for now. Let's say I have
quantity w as
a function of say variables x and y.
And so in the previous setup x and y depended
on some
parameters t. But, actually,
let's now look at the case where x and y themselves
are
functions of several variables. Let's say
of two more variables.
Let's call them u and v.
I am going to stay with these
abstract letters, but if it bothers you,
if it sounds completely unmotivated think
about it maybe
in terms of something you might now.
Say, polar coordinates. Let's say that I have
a
function but is defined in terms of the polar
coordinate
variables on theta. And then I know I want
to
switch to usual coordinates x and y.
Or, the other way around, I have a function
of x and y
and I want to express it in terms of the polar
coordinates r
and theta. Then I would want to know maybe
how the derivatives, with respect to the various
sets of variables, related to each other.
One way I could do it is, of course,
to say now if I plug the formula for x and
the formula
for y into the formula for f then w becomes
a function of u
and v, and it can try to take partial
derivatives. If I have explicit formulas,
well, that could work. But maybe the formulas
are
complicated. Typically, if I switch between
rectangular and polar coordinates,
there might be inverse trig, there might be
maybe arctangent
to express the polar angle in terms of x and
y.
And when I don't really want to actually substitute
arctangents
everywhere, maybe I would rather deal with
the derivatives.
How do I do that? The question is what are
partial w over partial u and partial w over
partial v in
terms of, let's see, what do we need to know
to
understand that? Well, probably we should
know
how w depends on x and y. If we don't know
that then we
are probably toast. Partial w over partial
x,
partial w over partial y should be required.
What else should we know? Well, it would probably
help to
know how x and y depend on u and v.
If we don't know that then we don't really
know how to do it.
We need also x sub u, x sub v, y sub u,
y sub v. We have a lot of partials in
there. Well, let's see how we can do
that. Let's start by writing dw.
We know that dw is partial f, well, I don't
know why I have
two names, w and f. I mean w and f are really
the
same thing here, but let's say f sub x dx
plus f
sub y dy. So far that is our new friend,
the differential. Now what do we want to do
with
it? Well, we would like to get rid
of dx and dy because we like to express things
in terms of,
you know, the question we are asking ourselves
is let's say
that I change u a little bit, how does w change?
Of course, what happens, if I change u a little
bit,
is y and y will change. How do they change?
Well, that is given to me by the differential.
dx is going to be, well, I can use the
differential again. Well, x is a function
of u and
v. That will be x sub u times du
plus x sub v times dv. That is, again,
taking the differential of a function of two
variables.
Does that make sense? And then we have the
other guy,
f sub y times, what is dy?
Well, similarly dy is y sub u du plus y sub
v dv.
And now we have a relation between dw and
du and dv.
We are expressing how w reacts to changes
in u and v,
which was our goal. Now, let's actually collect
terms so that we see it a bit better.
It is going to be f sub x times x sub u times
f sub y times y
sub u du plus f sub x, x sub v plus f sub
y y sub v
dv. Now we have dw equals something
du plus something dv. Well, the coefficient
here has
to be partial f over partial u. What else
could it be?
That's the rate of change of w with respect
to u if I forget
what happens when I change v. That is the
definition of a
partial. Similarly, this one has to be
partial f over partial v. That is because
it is the rate
of change with respect to v, if I keep u constant,
so that these guys are completely ignored.
Now you see how the total differential accounts
for,
somehow, all the partial derivatives that
come as
coefficients of the individual variables in
these expressions.
Let me maybe rewrite these formulas in a more
visible way
and then re-explain them to you. Here is the
chain rule for this
situation, with two intermediate variables
and two variables that
you express these in terms of. In our setting,
we get partial f over partial u equals partial
f over partial x
time partial x over partial u plus partial
f over partial y
times partial y over partial u. And the other
one,
the same thing with v instead of u,
partial f over partial x times partial x over
partial v plus
partial f over partial u partial y over partial
v.
I have to explain various things about these
formulas
because they look complicated. And, actually,
they are not that complicated. A couple of
things to know.
The first thing, how do we remember a formula
like that? Well, that is easy.
We want to know how f depends on u.
Well, what does f depend on? It depends on
x and y.
So we will put partial f over partial x and
partial f over
partial y. Now, x and y, why are they here?
Well, they are here because they actually
depend on u as
well. How does x depend on u?
Well, the answer is partial x over partial
u.
How does y depend on u? The answer is partial
y over
partial u. See, the structure of this
formula is simple. To find the partial of
f with
respect to some new variable you use the partials
with respect to
the variables that f was initially defined
in terms of x
and y. And you multiply them by the
partials of x and y in terms of the new variable
that you want
to look at, v here, and you sum these things
together. That is the structure of the
formula. Why does it work?
Well, let me explain it to you in a slightly
different
language. This asks us how does f change
if I change u a little bit? Well, why would
f change if u
changes a little bit? Well, it would change
because f
actually depends on x and y and x and y depend
on u.
If I change u, how quickly does x change?
Well, the answer is partial x over partial
u.
And now, if I change x at this rate, how does
that have to
change? Well, the answer is partial f
over partial x times this guy. Well, at the
same time,
y is also changing. How fast is y changing
if I
change u? Well, at the rate of partial y
over partial u. But now if I change this how
does f change? Well, the rate of change is
partial f over partial y. The product is the
effect of
how you change it, changing u, and therefore
changing f. Now, what happens in real life,
if I change u a little bit? Well, both x and
y change at
the same time. So how does f change?
Well, it is the sum of the two effects.
Does that make sense? Good.
Of course, if f depends on more variables
then you just have
more terms in here. OK.
Here is another thing that may be a little
bit confusing.
What is tempting? Well, what is tempting here
would be to simplify these formulas by removing
these
partial x's. Let's simplify by partial x.
Let's simplify by partial y. We get partial
f over partial u
equals partial f over partial u plus partial
f over partial u.
Something is not working properly.
Why doesn't it work? The answer is precisely
because
these are partial derivatives. These are not
total derivatives.
And so you cannot simplify them in that way.
And that is actually the reason why we use
this curly d rather
than a straight d. It is to remind us,
beware, there are these simplifications that
we can do
with straight d's that are not legal here.
Somehow, when you have a partial derivative,
you must resist the urge of simplifying things.
No simplifications in here. That is the simplest
formula
you can get. Any questions at this point?
No. Yes?
When would you use this and what does it describe?
Well, it is basically when you have a function
given in terms
of a certain set of variables because maybe
there is a simply
expression in terms of those variables.
But ultimately what you care about is not
those variables,
z and y, but another set of variables, here
u and v.
So x and y are giving you a nice formula for
f,
but actually the relevant variables for your
problem are u
and v. And you know x and y are
related to u and v. So, of course,
what you could do is plug the formulas the
way that we did
substituting. But maybe that will give you
very complicated expressions. And maybe it
is actually easier
to just work with the derivates. The important
claim here is
basically we don't need to know the actual
formulas.
All we need to know are the rate of changes.
If we know all these rates of change then
we know how to take
these derivatives without actually having
to plug in
values. Yes?
Yes, you could certain do the same things
in terms of t.
If x and y were functions of t instead of
being functions of u
and v then it would be the same thing.
And you would have the same formulas that
I had,
well, over there I still have it.
Why does that one have straight d's?
Well, the answer is I could put curly d's
if I wanted,
but I end up with a function of a single variable.
If you have a single variable then the partial,
with respect to that variable, is the same
thing as the usual
derivative. We don't actually need to worry
about curly in that case. But that one is
indeed special
case of this one where instead of x and y
depending on two
variables, u and v, they depend on a single
variable t. Now, of course,
you can call variables any name you want.
It doesn't matter. This is just a slight
generalization of that. Well, not quite because
here I
also had a z. See, I am trying to just
confuse you by giving you functions that depend
on various
numbers of variables. If you have a function
of 30
variables, things work the same way, just
longer,
and you are going to run out of letters in
the alphabet before
the end. Any other questions?
No. What?
Yes? If u and v themselves depended
on another variable then you would continue
with your chain
rules. Maybe you would know to express
partial x over partial u in terms using that
chain rule.
Sorry. If u and v are dependent on yet
another variable then you could get the derivative
with respect
to that using first the chain rule to pass
from u v to that
new variable, and then you would plug in
these formulas for partials of f with respect
to u and v.
In fact, if you have several substitutions
to do,
you can always arrange to use one chain rule
at a time.
You just have to do them in sequence.
That's why we don't actually learn that, but
you can just do
it be repeating the process. I mean, probably
at that stage,
the easiest to not get confused actually is
to manipulate
differentials because that is probably easier.
Yes? Curly f does not exist.
That's easy. Curly f makes no sense by
itself. It doesn't exist alone.
What exists is only curly df over curly d
some variable.
And then that accounts only for the rate of
change with respect
to that variable leaving the others fixed,
while straight df is somehow a total variation
of f.
It accounts for all of the partial derivatives
and their
combined effects. OK. Any more questions?
No.
Let me just finish up very quickly by telling
you again one
example where completely you might want to
do this.
You have a function that you want to switch
between
rectangular and polar coordinates.
To make things a little bit concrete.
If you have polar coordinates that means in
the plane,
instead of using x and y, you will use coordinates
r,
distance to the origin, and theta, the angles
from the
x-axis. The change of variables for
that is x equals r cosine theta and y equals
r sine theta.
And so that means if you have a function f
that depends on x and
y, in fact, you can plug these in as a function
of r and theta.
Then you can ask yourself, well, what is partial
f over
partial r? And that is going to be,
well, you want to take partial f over partial
x times partial x
partial r plus partial f over partial y times
partial y over
partial r. That will end up being actually
f sub x times cosine theta plus f sub y times
sine theta.
And you can do the same thing to find partial
f,
partial theta. And so you can express
derivatives either in terms of x, y or in
terms of r and theta
with simple relations between them.
And the one last thing I should say.
On Thursday we will learn about more tricks
we can play with
variations of functions. And one that is important,
because you need to know it actually to do
the p-set,
is the gradient vector. The gradient vector
is simply a
vector. You use this downward pointing
triangle as the notation for the gradient.
It is simply is a vector whose components
are the partial
derivatives of a function. I mean, in a way,
you can think of a differential as a way to
package partial
derivatives together into some weird object.
Well, the gradient is also a way to package
partials
together. We will see on Thursday what it
is good for, but some of the problems on the
p-set use it.