The following content is provided under a
Creative
Commons license. Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer high quality
educational
resources for free. To make a donation or
to view
additional materials from hundreds of MIT
courses,
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at ocw.mit.edu.
So, basically the last few weeks, we've been
doing
derivatives. Now, we're going to integrals.
So -- OK, so more precisely, we are going
to be talking
about double integrals. OK, so just to motivate
the
notion, let me just remind you that
when you have a function of one variable -- -- say,
f of x, and you take its integrals
from, say, a to b of f of x dx,
well, that corresponds to the area below the
graph of f over
the interval from a to b. OK, so the picture
is something
like you have a; you have b.
You have the graph of f, and then what the
integral
measures is the area of this region.
And, when we say the area of this region,
of course,
if f is positive, that's what happens.
If f is negative, then we count negatively
the
area below the x axis. OK, so, now,
when you have a function of two variables,
then you can try to
do the same thing. Namely, you can plot its
graph.
Its graph will be a surface in space.
And then, we can try to look for the volume
below the graph.
And that's what we will call the double integral
of the
function over a certain region. OK, so let's
say that we have a
function of two variables, x and y.
Then, we'll look at the volume that's below
the graph z equals
f of xy. OK, so, let's draw a picture
for what this means. I have a function of
x and y.
I can draw its graph. The graph will be the
surface
with equation z equals f of x and y.
And, well, I have to decide where I will integrate
the
function. So, for that,
I will choose some region in the xy plane.
And, I will integrate the function on that
region.
So, it's over a region, R, in the xy plane.
So, I have this region R and I look at the
piece of the graph
that is above this region. And, we'll try
to compute the
volume of this solid here. OK, that's what
the double
integral will measure. So, we'll call that
integral of our region, R, of f of xy dA and
I will
have to explain what the notation means.
So, dA here stands for a piece of area.
A stands for area. And, well, it's a double
integral. So, that's why we have two
integral signs. And, we'll have to indicate
somehow the region over which we are integrating.
OK, we'll come up with more concrete notations
when we see
how to actually compute these things.
That's the basic definition. OK, so actually,
how do we define it, that's not really much
of a
definition yet. How do we actually define
this
rigorously? Well, remember,
the integral in one variable, you probably
saw a definition
where you take your integral from a to b,
and you cut it into little pieces.
And then, for each little piece, you take
the value of a
function, and you multiply by the width of
a piece.
That gives you a rectangular slice, and then
you sum all of
these rectangular slices together.
So, here we'll do the same thing.
So, well, let me put a picture up and explain
what it does.
So, we're going to cut our origin into little
pieces,
say, little rectangles or actually anything
we want.
And then, for each piece, with the small area,
delta A,
we'll take the area delta a times the value
of a function in
there that will give us the volume of a small
box that sits
under the graph. And then, we'll add all these
boxes together. That gives us an estimate
of a
volume. And then, to get actually the
integral, the integral will be defined as
a limit as we subdivide into smaller and smaller
boxes,
and we sum more and more pieces,
OK? So, actually,
what we do, oh, I still have a board here.
So, the actual definition involves cutting
R into small
pieces
of area that's called delta A or maybe delta
Ai,
the area of the i'th piece. And then, OK,
so maybe in the xy plane, we have our region,
and we'll cut it may be using some grade.
OK, and then we'll have each small piece.
Each small piece will have area delta Ai and
it will be at some
point, let's call it xi, yi ...
yi, xi. And then, we'll consider the
sum over all the pieces of f at that point,
xi,
yi times the area of a small piece.
So, what that corresponds to in the three-dimensional
picture is
just I sum the volumes of all of these little
columns that sit
under the graph. OK, and then,
so what I do is actually I take the limit
as the size of the
pieces tends to zero. So, I have more and
more
smaller and smaller pieces. And, that gives
me the double
integral. OK, so that's not a very good
sentence, but whatever. So, OK, so that's
the
definition. Of course, we will have to see
how to compute it. We don't actually compute
it.
When you compute an integral in single variable
calculus,
you don't do that. You don't cut into little
pieces and sum the pieces together.
You've learned how to integrate functions
using various
formulas, and similarly here,
we'll learn how to actually compute these
things without
doing that cutting into small pieces.
OK, any questions first about the concept,
or what the
definition is? Yes?
Well, so we'll have to learn which tricks
work,
and how exactly. But, so what we'll do actually
is we'll reduce the calculation of a double
integral to two
calculations of single integrals.
And so, for V, certainly, all the tricks
you've learned in single variable calculus
will come in
handy. OK, so,
yeah that's a strong suggestion that if you've
forgotten
everything about single variable calculus,
now would be a good time to actually brush
up on integrals.
The usual integrals, and the usual substitution
tricks and easy trig in particular, these
would be very
useful. OK, so, yeah,
how do we compute these things? That's what
we would have to
come up with. And, well,
going back to what we did with derivatives,
to understand variations of functions and
derivatives,
what we did was really we took slices parallel
to an axis or
another one. So, in fact,
here, the key is also the same. So, what we
are going to do is
instead of cutting into a lot of small boxes
like that and
summing completely at random, we will actually
somehow scan
through our region by parallel planes,
OK? So, let me put up,
actually, a slightly different picture up
here.
So, what I'm going to do is I'm going to take
planes,
say in this picture, parallel to the yz plane.
I'll take a moving plane that scans from the
back to the front
or from the front to the back. So, that means
I set the value
of x, and I look at the slice, x equals x0,
and then I will do that for all values of
x0.
So, now in each slice, well, I get what looks
a lot
like a single variable integral. OK, and that
integral will tell
me, what is the area in this? Well, I guess
it's supposed to
be green, but it all comes as black, so, let's
say the black
shaded slice. And then, when I add all of
these areas together, as the value of x changes,
I will get the volume. OK, let me try to explain
that
again. So, to compute this integral,
what we do is actually we take slices.
So, let's consider, let's call s of x the
area of a
slice, well, by a plane parallel to the yz
plane.
OK, so on the picture, s of x is just the
area of this
thing in the vertical wall. Now, if you sum
all of these,
well, why does that work? So, if you take
the origin
between two parallel slices that are very
close to each other,
what's the volume in these two things?
Well, it's essentially s of x times the thickness
of this very
thin slice, and the thickness would be
delta x0 dx if you take a limit with more
and more slices.
OK, so the volume will be the integral of
s of x dx from,
well, what should be the range for x?
Well, we would have to start at the very lowest
value of x that
ever happens in our origin, and we'd have
to go all the way
to the very largest value of x, from the very
far back to the
very far front. So, in this picture,
we probably start over here at the back, and
we'd end over here
at the front. So, let me just say from the
minimum, x, to the maximum x.
And now, how do we find S of x?
Well, S of x will be actually again an integral.
But now, it's an integral of the variable,
y, because when we look at this slice, what
changes from left to
right is y. So, well let me actually write
that down. For a given,
x, the area S of x you can compute as an integral
of f of
x, y dy. OK, well, now x is a constant,
and y will be the variable of integration.
What's the range for y? Well, it's from the
leftmost
point here to the rightmost point here on
the given slice.
So, there is a big catch here. That's a very
important thing
to remember. What is the range of
integration? The range of integration for
y
depends actually on x. See, if I take the
slice that's
pictured on that diagram, then the range for
y goes all
the way from the very left to the very right.
But, if I take a slice that, say, near the
very front,
then in fact, only a very small segment of
it
will be in my region. So, the range of values
for y
will be much less. Let me actually draw a
2D
picture for that. So, remember,
we fix x, so, sorry, so we fix a value of
x.
OK, and for a given value of x, what we will
do is we'll slice
our graph by this plane parallel to the yz
plane.
So, now we mention the graph is sitting above
that.
OK, that's the region R. We have the region,
R, and I have the graph of a function above
this region,
R. And, I'm trying to find the
area between this segment and the graph above
it in this
vertical plane. Well, to do that,
I have to integrate from y going from here
to here.
I want the area of a piece that sits above
this red segment.
And, so in particular, the endpoints,
the extreme values for y depend on x because,
see, if I slice here instead,
well, my bounds for y will be smaller.
OK, so now, if I put the two things together,
what I will get -- --
is actually a formula where I have
to integrate -- -- over x -- -- an integral
over y.
OK, and so this is called an iterated integral
because we
iterate twice the process of taking an integral.
OK, so again, what's important to realize
here, I mean, I'm going to say that
several times over the next few days but that's
because it's the
single most important thing to remember about
double integrals,
the bounds here are just going to be numbers,
OK, because the question I'm asking myself
here is,
what is the first value of x by which I might
want to slice,
and what is the last value of x? Which range
of x do I want to
look at to take my red slices? And, the answer
is I would go
all the way from here, that's my first slice,
to somewhere here. That's my last slice.
For any value in between these, I will have
some red segment,
and I will want to integrate over that that.
On the other hand here, the bounds will depend
on the
outer variable, x,
because at a fixed value of x, what the values
of y will be
depends on x in general. OK, so I think we
should do
lots of examples to convince ourselves and
see how it works.
Yeah, it's called an iterated integral because
first we
integrated over y, and then we integrate again
over x, OK? So, we can do that,
well, I mean, y depends on x or x depends,
no, actually x and y vary independently of
each other
inside here. What is more complicated is how
the bounds on y depend on x. But actually,
you could also do the other way around: first
integrate over x,
and then over y, and then the bounds for x
will
depend on y. We'll see that on an example.
Yes? So, for y, I'm using the range
of values for y that corresponds to the given
value of x,
OK? Remember, this is just like a
plot in the xy plane. Above that, we have
the graph.
Maybe I should draw a picture here instead.
For a given value of x, so that's a given
slice,
I have a range of values for y, that is,
from this picture at the leftmost point on
that slice to
the rightmost point on that slice.
So, where start and where I stop depends on
the value of x.
Does that make sense? OK.
OK, no more questions? OK, so let's do our
first
example. So, let's say that we want to
integrate the function 1-x^2-y^2 over the
region defined by x
between 0 and 1, and y between 0 and 1.
So, what does that mean geometrically?
Well, z = 1-x^2-y^2, and it's a variation
on,
actually I think we plotted that one, right?
That was our first example of a function of
two variables
possibly. And, so, we saw that the graph
is this paraboloid pointing downwards.
OK, it's what you get by taking a parabola
and rotating it.
And now, what we are asking is, what is the
volume between the
paraboloid and the xy plane over the square
of side one in the xy
plane over the square of side one in the xy
plane,
x and y between zero and one. OK, so, what
we'll do is we'll,
so, see, here I try to represent the square.
And, we'll just sum the areas of the slices
as,
say, x varies from zero to one. And here,
of course,
setting up the bounds will be easy because
no matter what x I
take, y still goes from zero to one.
See, it's easiest to do double integrals what
the region is
just a rectangle on the xy plane because then
you don't have to
worry too much about what are the ranges.
OK, so let's do it. Well, that would be the
integral from zero to one of the integral
from zero to one of
1-x^2-y^2 dy dx. So, I'm dropping the
parentheses. But, if you still want to see
them, I'm going to put that in very thin so
that you see what
it means. But, actually,
the convention is we won't put this parentheses
in there
anymore. OK, so what this means is first
I will integrate 1-x^2-y^2 over y, ranging
from zero to one with
x held fixed. So, what that represents is
the
area in this slice. So, see here,
I've drawn, well, what happens is actually
the
function takes positive and negative values.
So, in fact, I will be counting positively
this part of the area. And, I will be counting
negatively this part of the area, I mean,
as usual when I do an integral. OK, so what
I will do to
evaluate this, I will first do what's called
the inner integral. So, to do the inner integral,
well, it's pretty easy. How do I integrate
this?
Well, it becomes, so, what's the integral
of one?
It's y. Just anything to remember is we
are integrating this with respect to y,
not to x. The integral of x^2 is x^2
times y. And, the integral of y^2 is y^3
over 3. OK, and that we plug in the
bounds, which are zero and one in this case.
And so, when you plug y equals one, you will
get one minus x^2
minus one third minus, well, for y equals
zero you get
0,0, 0, so nothing changes. OK, so you are
left with two
thirds minus x^2. OK, and that's a function
of x
only. Here, you shouldn't see any y's
anymore because y was your integration variable.
But, you still have x. You still have x because
the
area of this shaded slice depends, of course,
on the value of x. And, so now,
the second thing to do is to do the outer
integral.
So, now we integrate from zero to one what
we got,
which is two thirds minus x^2 dx.
OK, and we know how to compute that because
that integrates to
two thirds x minus one third x^3 between zero
and one.
And, I'll let you do the computation.
You will find it's one third. OK, so that's
the final answer.
So, that's the general pattern. When we have
a double integral
to compute, first we want to set it up carefully.
We want to find, what will be the bounds in
x
and y? And here, that was actually
pretty easy because our equation was very
simple.
Then, we want to compute the inner integral,
and then we compute the outer integral.
And, that's it. OK, any questions at this
point?
No? OK, so, by the way,
we started with dA in the notation, right?
Here we had dA. And, that somehow became a
dy
dx. OK,
so, dA became dy dx because when we
do the iterated integral this way,
what we're actually doing is that we are slicing
our origin
into small rectangles. OK, that was the area
of this
small rectangle here? Well, it's the product
of its
width times its height. So, that's delta x
times delta
y. OK, so, delta a equals delta x
delta y becomes... So actually,
it's not just becomes, it's really equal.
So, the small rectangles for. Now, it became
dy dx and not dx
dy. Well, that's a question of,
in which order we do the iterated integral?
It's up to us to decide whether we want to
integrate x first,
then y, or y first, then x.
But, as we'll see very soon, that is an important
decision
when it comes to setting up the bounds of
integration.
Here, it doesn't matter, but in general we
have to be
very careful about in which order we
will do things.
Yes? Well, in principle it always
works both ways. Sometimes it will be that
because the region has a strange shape, you
can actually set it
up more easily one way or the other.
Sometimes it will also be that the function
here,
you actually know how to integrate in one
way,
but not the other. So, the theory is that
it
should work both ways. In practice,
one of the two calculations may be much harder.
OK. Let's do another example.
Let's say that what I wanted to know was not
actually what I
computed, namely, the volume below the
paraboloid, but also the negative of some
part that's now in the corner towards me.
But let's say really what I wanted was just
the volume
between the paraboloid and the xy plane,
so looking only at the part of it that sits
above the xy plane.
So, that means, instead of integrating over
the
entire square of size one, I should just integrate
over
the quarter disk. I should stop integrating
where
my paraboloid hits the xy plane. So, let me
draw another picture.
So, let's say I wanted to integrate, actually
-- So,
let's call this example two. So, we are going
to do the same
function but over a different region.
And, the region will just be, now, this quarter
disk here.
OK, so maybe I should draw a picture on the
xy plane.
That's your region, R. OK, so in principle,
it will be the same integral. But what changes
is the bounds.
Why do the bounds change? Well, the bounds
change because
now if I set, if I fixed some value of x,
then I want to integrate this part of the
slice that's above
the xy plane and I don't want to take this
part that's actually
outside of my disk. So, I should stop integrating
over y when y reaches this value here.
OK, on that picture here, on this picture,
it tells me for a fixed value of x, the range
of values for y
should go only from here to here.
So, that's from here to less than one.
OK, so for a given, x, the range of y is,
well, so what's the lowest value of y that
we want to look
at? It's still zero.
From y equals zero to,what's the value of
y here?
Well, I have to solve in the equation of a
circle,
OK? So, if I'm here,
this is x^2 y^2 equals one. That means y is
square root of
one minus x^2. OK, so I will integrate from
y
equals zero to y equals square root of one
minus x^2.
And, now you see how the bound from y will
depend on the value
of x. OK, so while I erase,
I will let you think about, what is the bound
for x now?
It's a trick question.
OK, so I claim that what we will do -- We
write this as an
iterated integral first dy then dx.
And, we said for a fixed value of x, the range
for y is from
zero to square root of one minus x^2.
What about the range for x? Well, the range
for x should
just be numbers. OK, remember,
the question I have to ask now is if I look
at all of these
yellow slices, which one is the first one
that
I will consider? Which one is the last one
I want to consider? So, the smallest value
of x
that I want to consider is zero again.
And then, I will have actually a pretty big
slice.
And I will get smaller, and smaller,
and smaller slices. And, it stops.
I have to stop when x equals one.
Afterwards, there's nothing else to integrate.
So, x goes from zero to one. OK, and now,
see how in the inner integral, the bounds
depend on in the
inner integral, the bounds depend on x.
In the outer one, you just get numbers because
the questions that you have to ask to set
up this one and set
up that one are different. Here, the question
is,
if I fix a given, x, if I look at a given
slice,
what's the range for y? Here, the question
is,
what's the first slice? What is the last slice?
Does that make sense? Everyone happy with
that?
OK, very good. So, now, how do we compute
Well, we do the inner integral. So, that's
an integral from
zero to square root of one minus x^2 of one
minus x^2 minus y^2
dy. And, well, that integrates to
y-x^2y-y^3 over three from zero to square
root of one minus x^2.
And then, that becomes, well, the root of
one minus x^2
minus x^2 root of one minus x^2 minus y minus
x^2 to the three
halves over three. And actually,
if you look at it for long enough, see, this
says one minus
x^2 times square root of one minus x^2.
So, actually, that's also,
so, in fact, that simplifies to two thirds
of one minus x^2 to the three halves.
OK, let me redo that, maybe, slightly differently.
This was one minus x^2 times y. So -- --
one minus x^2 times y
becomes square root of one minus x^2 minus
y^3 over three.
And then, when I take y equals zero, I get
zero.
So, I don't subtract anything. OK, so now
you see this is one
minus x^2 to the three halves minus a third
of it.
So, you're left with two thirds. OK, so, that's
the integral.
The outer integral is the integral from zero
to one of two
thirds of one minus x^2 to the three halves
dx.
And, well,
I let you see if you remember single variable
integrals by
trying to figure out what this actually comes
out to be is it
pi over two, or pi over eight, actually?
I think it's pi over eight. OK, well I guess
we have to do
it then. I wrote something on my notes,
but it's not very clear, OK?
So, how do we compute this thing?
Well, we have to do trig substitution.
That's the only way I know to compute an integral
like that,
OK? So, we'll set x equal sine
theta, and then square root of one minus x^2
will be cosine
theta. We are using sine squared plus
cosine squared equals one. And, so that will
become -- --
so, two thirds remains two thirds.
One minus x^2 to the three halves becomes
cosine cubed
theta. dx, well, if x is sine theta,
then dx is cosine theta d theta.
So, that's cosine theta d theta. And,
well, if you do things with substitution,
which is the way I do them, then you should
worry about the
bounds for theta which will be zero to pi
over two.
Or, you can also just plug in the bounds at
the end.
So, now you have the two thirds times the
integral from zero to
pi over two of cosine to the fourth theta
d theta.
And, how do you integrate that? Well, you
have to use double
angle formulas. OK, so cosine to the fourth,
remember, cosine squared theta is one plus
cosine two theta
over two. And, we want the square of that.
And, so that will give us -- -- of,
well, we'll have, it's actually one quarter
plus
one half cosine to theta plus one quarter
cosine square to
theta d theta. And, how will you handle this
guy? Well, using,
again, the double angle formula.
OK, so it's getting slightly nasty.
So, but I don't know any simpler solution
except for one
simpler solution, which is you have a table
of
integrals of this form inside the notes.
Yes? No, I don't think so because if
you take one half times cosine half times
two,
you will still have half, OK?
So, if you do, again, the double angle
formula, I think I'm not going to bother to
do it.
I claim you will get, at the end, pi over
eight
because I say so. OK, so exercise,
continue calculating and get pi over eight.
OK, now what does the show us? Well, this
shows us,
actually, that this is probably not the right
way to do this.
OK, the right way to do this will be to integrate
it in polar
coordinates. And, that's what we will learn
how to do tomorrow. So, we will actually see
how to
do it with much less trig.
So, that will be easier in polar coordinates.
So, we will see that tomorrow. OK, so we are
almost there.
I mean, here you just use a double angle again
and then you
can get it. And, it's pretty
straightforward. OK, so one thing that's kind
of
interesting to know is we can exchange the
order of
integration. Say we have an integral given
to us in the order dy dx, we can switch it
to dx dy.
But, we have to be extremely careful with
the bounds.
So, you certainly cannot just swap the bounds
of the inner and
outer because there you would end up having
this square root
of one minus x^2 on the outside, and you would
never get a
number out of that. So, that cannot work.
It's more complicated than that. OK, so, well,
here's a first baby example. Certainly, if
I do integral
from zero to one, integral from zero to two
dx
dy, there, I can certainly switch the bounds
without
thinking too much. What's the reason for that?
Well, the reason for that is this corresponds
in both cases
to integrating x from zero to two, and y from
zero to one.
It's a rectangle. So, if I slice it this way,
you see that y goes from zero to one for any
x between zero
and two. It's this guy.
If I slice it that way, then x goes from zero
to two
for any value of y between zero and one.
And, it's this one. So, here it works.
But in general, I have to draw picture of
my
region, and see how the slices look like both
ways.
OK, so let's do a more interesting one.
Let's say that I want to compute an integral
from zero to
one of integral from x to square root of x
of e^y over y dy dx.
So, why did I choose this guy? Which is the
guy because as far
as I can tell, there's no way to integrate
e^y
over y. So, this is an integral that
you cannot compute this way. So, it's a good
example for why
this can be useful. So, if you do it this
way,
you are stuck immediately. So, instead,
we will try to switch the order.
But, to switch the order, we have to understand,
what do these bounds mean? OK, so let's draw
a picture of
the region. Well what I am saying is y
equals x to y equals square root of x.
Well, let's draw y equals x, and y equals
square root of x.
Well, maybe I should actually put this here,
y equals x to y equals square root of x.
OK, and so I will go, for each value of x
I will go
from y equals xo to y equals square root of
x.
And then, we'll do that for values of x that
go from x
equals zero to x equals one, which happens
to be exactly
where these things intersect. So, my region
will consist of
all this, OK? So now, if I want to do it the
other way around, I have to decompose my region.
The other way around, I have to, so my goal,
now, is to rewrite this as an integral.
Well, it's still the same function.
It's still e to the y over y. But now, I want
to integrate dx
dy. So, how do I integrate over x?
Well, I fix a value of y. And, for that value
of y,
what's the range of x? Well, the range for
x is from
here to here. OK, what's the value of x here?
Let's start with an easy one. This is x equals
y.
What about this one? It's x equals y^2.
OK, so, x goes from y2 to y, and then what
about y?
Well, I have to start at the bottom of my
region.
That's y equals zero to the top, which is
at y equals one.
So, y goes from zero to one. So, switching
the bounds is not
completely obvious. That took a little bit
of work.
But now that we've done that, well,
just to see how it goes, it's actually going
to be much
easier to integrate because the inner integral,
well, what's the integral of e^y over y with
respect to x?
It's just that times x, right, from x equals
y^2 to y.
So, that will be, well, if I plug x equals
y,
I will get e to the y minus, if I plug x equals
y^2,
I will get e to the y over y times y^2 into
the y times y,
OK? So, now, if I do the outer
integral, I will have the integral from zero
to one of e
to the y minus y^e to the y dy. And, that
one actually is a
little bit easier. So, we know how to integrate
e^y. We don't quite know how to
integrate ye^y. But, let's try.
So, let's see, what's the derivative of ye^y?
Well, there's a product rule that's one times
e^y plus y
times the derivative of e^y is ye^y.
So, if we do, OK, let's put a minus sign in
front. Well, that's almost what we
want, except we have a minus e^y instead of
a plus e^y.
So, we need to add 2e^y. And, I claim that's
the
antiderivative. OK, if you got lost,
you can also integrate by integrating by parts,
by taking the derivative of y and integrating
these guys.
Or, but, you know, that works. Just, your
first guess would
be, maybe, let's try minus y^e to the y.
Take the derivative of that, compare, see
what you need to
do to fix. And so, if you take that
between zero and one, you'll actually get
e minus
two. OK,
so, tomorrow we are going to see
how to do double integrals in polar coordinates,
and also applications of double integrals,
how to use them for interesting things.