The following content is provided under a
Creative
Commons license. Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer high quality
educational
resources for free. To make a donation or
to view
additional materials from hundreds of MIT
courses,
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at ocw.mit.edu.
So, today we are going to continue looking
at critical
points, and we'll learn how to actually
decide whether a typical point is a minimum,
maximum, or a saddle point. So, that's the
main topic for
today. So, remember yesterday,
we looked at critical points of functions
of several variables.
And, so a critical point functions, we have
two values,
x and y. That's a point where the
partial derivatives are both zero.
And, we've seen that there's various kinds
of critical
points. There's local minima.
So, maybe I should show the function on this
contour
plot,there is local maxima, which are like
that.
And, there's saddle points which are neither
minima nor
maxima. And, of course,
if you have a real function, then it would
be more
complicated. It will have several critical
points. So, this example here,
well, you see on the plot that there is two
maxima.
And, there is in the middle, between them,
a saddle point. And, actually,
you can see them on the contour plot.
On the contour plot, you see the maxima because
the
level curves become circles that now down
and shrink to the
maximum. And, you can see the saddle
point because here you have this level curve
that makes a figure
eight. It crosses itself.
And, if you move up or down here, so along
the y direction,
the values of the function will decrease.
Along the x direction, the values will increase.
So, you can see usually quite easily where
are the critical
points just by looking either at the graph
or at the contour
plots. So, the only thing with the
contour plots is you need to read the values
to tell a
minimum from a maximum because the contour
plots look the same.
Just, of course, in one case,
the values increase, and in another one they
decrease. So, the question -- -- is,
how do we decide -- --
between the various possibilities?
So, local minimum, local maximum,
or saddle point.
So, and, in fact, why do we care?
Well, the other question is how do we find
the global
minimum/maximum of a function? So, here what
I should point
out, well, first of all,
to decide where the function is the largest,
in general you'll have actually to compare
the values.
For example, here, if you want to know,
what is the maximum of this function?
Well, we have two obvious candidates.
We have this local maximum and that local
maximum.
And, the question is, which one is the higher
of the
two? Well, in this case,
actually, there is actually a tie for maximum.
But, in general, you would have to compute
the
function at both points, and compare the values
if you
know that it's three at one of them and four
at the other.
Well, four wins. The other thing that you
see
here is if you are looking for the minimum
of this function,
well, the minimum is not going to be at any
of the critical
points. So, where's the minimum?
Well, it looks like the minimum is actually
out there on the
boundary or at infinity. So, that's another
feature.
The global minimum or maximum doesn't have
to be at a critical
point. It could also be,
somehow, on the side in some limiting situation
where one
variable stops being in the allowed rang of
values or goes
to infinity. So, we have to actually check
the boundary and the infinity behavior of
our function to know
where, actually, the minimum and maximum will
be. So, in general,
I should point out, these should occur either
at
the critical point or on the boundary or at
infinity.
So, by that, I mean on the boundary of a
domain of definition that we are considering.
And so, we have to try both. OK, but so we'll
get back to
that. For now, let's try to focus on
the question of, you know, what's the type
of
the critical point? So, we'll use something
that's
known as the second derivative test.
And, in principle, well, the idea is kind
of
similar to what you do with the function of
one variable,
namely, the function of one variable.
If the derivative is zero, then you know that
you should
look at the second derivative. And, that will
tell you whether
it's curving up or down whether you have a
local max and the
local min. And, the main problem here is,
of course, we have more possible situations,
and we have several derivatives.
So, we have to think a bit harder about how
we'll decide.
But, it will again involve the second derivative.
OK, so let's start with just an easy example
that will be useful
to us because actually it will provide the
basis for the
general method. OK, so we are first going
to
consider a case where we have a function that's
actually just
quadratic. So, let's say I have a
function, W of (x,y) that's of the form ax^2
bxy cy^2.
OK, so this guy has a critical point at the
origin because if
you take the derivative with respect to x,
well, and if you plug x equals y equals zero,
you'll get zero, and same with respect to
y.
You can also see, if you try to do a linear
approximation of this, well, all these guys
are much
smaller than x and y when x and y are small.
So, the linear approximation, the tangent
plane to the graph
is really just w=0. OK, so, how do we do it?
Well, yesterday we actually did an example.
It was a bit more complicated than that, but
let me do it,
so remember, we were looking at something
that started with x^2 2xy 3y^2. And, there
were other terms.
But, let's forget them now. And, what we did
is we said,
well, we can rewrite this as (x y)^2 2y^2.
And now, this is a sum of two squares.
So, each of these guys has to be nonnegative.
And so, the origin will be a minimum.
Well, it turns out we can do something similar
in general no
matter what the values of a, b, and c are.
We'll just try to first complete things to
a square.
OK, so let's do that. So, in general,
well, let me be slightly less general, and
let me assume that
a is not zero because otherwise I can't do
what I'm going to do.
So, I'm going to write this as a times x^2
plus b over axy.
And then I have my cy^2. And now this looks
like the
beginning of the square of something, OK,
just like what we did over there.
So, what is it the square of? Well, you'd
start with x plus I
claim if I put b over 2a times y and I square
it,
then see the cross term two times x times
b over 2a y will
become b over axy. Of course, now I also get
some
y squares out of this. How many y squares
do I get?
Well, I get b^2 over 4a^2 times a.
So, I get b2 over 4a y^2. So, and I want,
in fact, c times y^2. So, the number of y^2
that I
should add is c minus b^2 over 4a.
OK, let's see that again. If I expand this
thing,
I will get ax^2 plus a times b over 2a times
2xy.
That's going to be my bxy. But, I also get
b^2 over 4a^2
y^2 times a. That's b^2 over 4ay^2.
And, that cancels out with this guy here.
And then, I will be left with cy^2.
OK, do you see it kind of? OK, if not, well,
try expanding this square again.
OK, maybe I'll do it just to convince you.
But, so if I expand this, I will get A times,
let me put that in a different color because
you shouldn't
write that down. It's just to convince you
again.
So, if you don't see it yet, let's expend
this thing.
We'll get a times x^2 plus a times 2xb over
2ay.
Well, the two A's cancel out. We get bxy plus
a times the
square of that's going to be b^2 over 4a^2
y^2 plus cy^2 minus
b^2 over 4ay^2. Here, the a and the a
simplifies, and now these two terms simplify
and give me just
cy^2 in the end. OK, and that's kind of
unreadable after I've canceled everything,
but if you follow it, you see that basically
I've
just rewritten my initial function.
OK, is that kind of OK? I mean, otherwise
there's just
no substitute. You'll have to do it yourself,
I'm afraid. OK, so, let me continue to play
with this. So, I'm just going to put this
in a slightly different form just to clear
the denominators.
OK, so, I will instead write this as one over
4a times the
big thing. So, I'm going to just put 4a^2
times x plus b over 2ay squared. OK, so far
I have the same
thing as here. I just introduced the 4a that
cancels out, plus for the other one, I'm just
clearing the
denominator. I end up with (4ac-b^2)y^2.
OK, so that's a lot of terms. But, what does
it look like?
Well, it looks like, so we have some constant
factors, and here we have a square, and here
we have a
square. So, basically,
we've written this as a sum of two squares,
well,
a sum or a difference of two squares.
And, maybe that's what we need to figure out
to know what kind
of point it is because, see, if you take a
sum of two
squares, that you will know that each
square takes nonnegative values. And you will
have,
the function will always take nonnegative
values.
So, the origin will be a minimum.
Well, if you have a difference of two squares
that typically
you'll have a saddle point because depending
on whether one
or the other is larger, you will have a positive
or a
negative quantity. OK, so I claim there's
various
cases to look at. So, let's see.
So, in fact, I claim there will be three
cases. And, that's good news for us
because after all, we want to distinguish
between
three possibilities. So, let's first do away
with
the most complicated one. What if 4ac minus
b^2 is
negative? Well, if it's negative,
then it means what I have between the brackets
is,
so the first guy is obviously a positive quantity,
while the second one will be something negative
times y2.
So, it will be a negative quantity.
OK, so one term is positive. The other is
negative.
That tells us we actually have a saddle point.
We have, in fact, written our function as
a
difference of two squares. OK, is that convincing?
So, if you want, what I could do is actually
I
could change my coordinates, have new coordinates
called u
equals x b over 2ay, and v, actually,
well, I could keep y, and that it would look
like the
difference of squares directly. OK, so that's
the first case.
The second case is where 4ac-b^2 = 0.
Well, what happens if that's zero?
Then it means that this term over there goes
away.
So, what we have is just one square.
OK, so what that means is actually that our
function
depends only on one direction of things.
In the other direction, it's going to actually
be
degenerate. So, for example,
forget all the clutter in there.
Say I give you just the function of two variables,
w equals just x^2. So, that means it doesn't
depend on y at all. And, if I try to plot
the
graph, it will look like, well, x is here.
So, it will depend on x in that way, but it
doesn't depend on y
at all. So, what the graph looks like
is something like that. OK, basically it's
a valley
whose bottom is completely flat. So, that
means,
actually, we have a degenerate critical point.
It's called degenerate because there is a
direction in which
nothing happens. And, in fact,
you have critical points everywhere along
the y axis.
Now, whether the square that we have is x
or something else,
namely, x plus b over 2a y, it doesn't matter.
I mean, it will still get this degenerate
behavior.
But there's a direction in which nothing happens
because we
just have the square of one quantity.
I'm sure that 300 students means 300 different
ring tones,
but I'm not eager to hear all of them, thanks.
[LAUGHTER] OK, so, this is what's called a
degenerate critical point, and [LAUGHTER].
OK, so basically we'll leave it here.
We won't actually try to figure out further
what happens,
and the reason for that is that when you have
an actual
function, a general function,
not just one that's quadratic like this,
then there will actually be other terms maybe
involving
higher powers, maybe x^3 or y^3 or things
like
that. And then, they will mess up
what happens in this valley. And, it's a situation
where we
won't be able, actually, to tell automatically
just by looking at second derivatives what
happens.
See, for example, in a function of one variable,
if you have just a function of one variable,
say, f of x equals x to the five,
well, if you try to decide what type of point
the origin is,
you're going to take the second derivative.
It will be zero, and then you can conclude.
Those things depend on higher order derivatives.
So, we just won't like that case.
We just won't try to figure out what's going
on here.
Now, the last situation is if 4ac-b^2 is positive.
So, then, that means that actually we've written
things.
The big bracket up there is a sum of two squares.
So, that means that we've written w as one
over 4a times
plus something squared plus something else
squared,
OK? So, these guys have the same
sign, and that means that this term here will
always be greater
than or equal to zero. And that means that
we should
either have a maximum or minimum.
How we find out which one it is? Well, we
look at the sign of a,
exactly. OK?
So, there's two sub-cases. One is if a is
positive,
then, this quantity overall will always be
nonnegative.
And that means we have a minimum, OK?
And, if a is negative on the other hand,
so that means that we multiply this positive
quantity by a
negative number, we get something that's always
negative. So, zero is actually the
maximum. OK, is that clear for everyone?
Yes? Sorry, yeah,
so I said in the example w equals x^2, it
doesn't depend on
y. So, the more general situation
is w equals some constant. Well, I guess it's
a times (x b
over 2a times y)^2. So, it does depend on
x and y,
but it only depends on this combination.
OK, so if I choose to move in some other perpendicular
direction, in the direction where this
remains constant, so maybe if I set x equals
minus b over 2a y, then this remains zero
all the
time. So, there's a degenerate
direction in which I stay at the minimum or
maximum,
or whatever it is that I have. OK, so that's
why it's called
degenerate. There is a direction in which
nothing happens. OK, yes?
Yes, yeah, so that's a very good question.
So, there's going to be the second derivative
test.
Why do not have derivatives yet? Well, that's
because I've been
looking at this special example where we have
a function like
this. And, so I don't actually need
to take derivatives yet. But, secretly,
that's because a, b, and c will be the second
derivatives of the function, actually, 2a,
b, and 2c. So now, we are going to go to
general function. And there, instead of having
these coefficients a, b, and c given to us,
we'll have to compute them as second derivatives.
OK, so here, I'm basically setting the stage
for what will be the actual criterion we'll
use using second
derivatives. Yes?
So, yeah, so what you have a degenerate critical
point,
it could be a degenerate minimum, or a degenerate
maximum
depending on the sign of a. But, in general,
once you start having functions, you don't
really know
what will happen anymore. It could also be
a degenerate
saddle, and so on. So, we won't really be
able to
tell. Yes?
It is possible to have a degenerate saddle
point.
For example, if I gave you x^3 y^3,
you can convince yourself that if you take
x and y to be
negative, it will be negative. If x and y
are positive,
it's positive. And, it has a very degenerate
critical point at the origin. So, that's a
degenerate saddle
point. We don't see it here because
that doesn't happen if you have only quadratic
terms like that.
You need to have higher-order terms to see
it happen.
OK. OK, so let's continue.
Before we continue, but see, I wanted to point
out
one small thing. So, here, we have the magic
quantity, 4ac minus b^2. You've probably seen
that
before in your life. Yet, it looks like the
quadratic formula, except that one involves
b^2-4ac. But that's really the same
thing. OK, so
let's see,
where does the quadratic formula come in here?
Well, let me write things differently.
OK, so we've manipulated things, and got into
a
conclusion. But, let me just do a different
manipulation, and write this now instead as
y^2 times a times x over y squared plus b(x
over y) plus c.
OK, see, that's the same thing that I had
before.
Well, so now this quantity here is always
nonnegative.
What about this one? Well, of course,
this one depends on x over y. It means it
depends on which
direction you're going to move away from the
origin,
which ratio between x and y you will consider.
But, I claim there's two situations.
One is, so, let's try to reformulate things.
So, if a discriminate here is positive, then
it means that
these have roots and these have solutions.
And, that means that this quantity can be
both positive
and negative. This quantity takes positive
and negative values. One way to convince yourself
is
just to, you know, plot at^2 bt c.
You know that there's two roots. So, it might
look like this,
or might look like that depending on the sign
of a.
But, in either case, it will take values of
both
signs. So, that means that your
function will take values of both signs.
The value takes both positive and negative
values.
And, so that means we have a saddle point,
while the other situation, when b^2-4ac is
negative -- --
means that this equation is quadratic never
takes the value,
zero. So, it's always positive or
it's always negative, depending on the sign
of a.
So, the other case is if b^2-4ac is negative,
then the quadratic doesn't have a solution.
And it could look like this or like that depending
on whether a
is positive or a is negative. So, in particular,
that means that ax over y2 plus bx over y
plus c is always
positive or always negative depending on the
sign of a.
And then, that tells us that our function,
w, will be always positive or always negative.
And then we'll get a minimum or maximum.
OK, we'll have a min or a max depending on
which situation we
are in. OK, so that's another way to
derive the same answer. And now, you see here
why the
discriminate plays a role. That's because
it exactly tells
you whether this quadratic quantity has always
the same
sign, or whether it can actually
cross the value, zero, when you have the root
of
a quadratic. OK, so hopefully at this stage
you are happy with one of the two explanations,
at least. And now, you are willing to
believe, I hope, that we have basically a
way of
deciding what type of critical point we have
in the special
case of a quadratic function.
OK, so, now what do we do with the general
function?
Well, so in general, we want to look at second
derivatives. OK, so now we are getting to
the real stuff. So, how many second derivatives
do we have? That's maybe the first thing we
should figure out. Well, we can take the
derivative first with respect to x, and then
again with respect
to x. OK, that gives us something we
denote by partial square f over partial x
squared or fxx.
Then, there's another one which is fxy, which
means you take the
derivative with respect to x, and then with
respect to y.
Another thing you can do, is do first derivative
respect
to y, and then with respect to x.
That would be fyx. Well, good news.
These are actually always equal to each other.
OK, so it's the fact that we will admit, it's
actually not
very hard to check. So these are always the
same.
We don't need to worry about which one we
do.
That's one computation that we won't need
to do.
We can save a bit of effort. And then, we
have the last one,
namely, the second partial with respect to
y and y fyy.
OK, so we have three of them. So, what does
the second
derivative test say?
It says, say that you have a critical point
(x0,
y0) of a function of two variables, f,
and then let's compute the partial derivatives.
So, let's call capital A the second derivative
with respect
to x. Let's call capital B the second
derivative with respect to x and y.
And C equals fyy at this point, OK?
So, these are just numbers because we first
compute the
second derivative, and then we plug in the
values
of x and y at the critical point.
So, these will just be numbers. And now, what
we do is we look
at the quantity AC-B^2. I am not forgetting
the four.
You will see why there isn't one.
So, if AC-B^2 is positive, then there's two
sub-cases.
If A is positive, then it's local minimum.
The
second case, so, still, if AC-B^2 is
positive, but A is negative, then it's going
to be a local
maximum. And, if AC-B^2 is negative,
then it's a saddle point, and finally,
if AC-B^2 is zero, then we actually cannot
compute. We don't know whether it's
going to be a minimum, a maximum, or a saddle.
We know it's degenerate in some way, but we
don't know what type
of point it is. OK, so that's actually what
you
need to remember. If you are formula oriented,
that's all you need to remember about today.
But, let's try to understand why, how this
comes out of what
we had there. OK, so, I think maybe I
actually want to keep, so maybe I want to
keep this
middle board because it actually has,
you know, the recipe that we found before
the quadratic
function. So, let me move directly over
there and try to relate our old recipe with
the new.
OK, you are easily amused. OK, so first,
let's check that these two things say the
same thing in the
special case that we are looking at.
OK, so let's verify in the special case where
the function
was ax^2 bxy cy^2. So -- Well, what is the
second
derivative with respect to x and x?
If I take the second derivative with respect
to x and x,
so first I want to take maybe the derivative
with respect to
x. But first, let's take the first
partial, Wx. That will be 2ax by, right?
So, Wxx will be, well, let's take a partial
with
respect to x again. That's 2a.
Wxy, I take the partial respect to y, and
we'll get b.
OK, now we need, also, the partial with respect
to y. So, Wy is bx 2cy.
In case you don't believe what I told you
about the mixed
partials, Wyx, well, you can check.
And it's, again, b. So, they are,
indeed, the same thing. And, Wyy will be 2c.
So, if we now look at these quantities, that
tells us,
well, big A is two little a, big B is little
b,
big C is two little c. So, AC-B^2 is what
we used to
call four little ac minus b2. OK, ooh.
[LAUGHTER] So, now you can compare the
cases. They are not listed in the same
order just to make it harder. So, we said
first,
so the saddle case is when AC-B^2 in big letters
is
negative, that's the same as 4ac-b2 in lower
case is
negative. The case where capital AC-B2 is
positive, local min and local max corresponds
to this one.
And, the case where we can't conclude was
what used to be the
degenerate one. OK, so at least we don't seem
to have messed up when copying the formula.
Now, why does that work more generally than
that?
Well, the answer that is, again, Taylor approximation.
Aww. OK, so let me just do here
quadratic approximation. So, quadratic approximation
tells me the following thing. It tells me,
if I have a function, f of xy, and I want
to
understand the change in f when I change x
and y a little bit.
Well, there's the first-order terms.
There is the linear terms that by now you
should know and be
comfortable with. That's fx times the change
in x.
And then, there's fy times the change in y.
OK, that's the starting point. But now, of
course,
if x and y, sorry, if we are at the critical
point, then that's going to be zero at the
critical point.
So, that term actually goes away, and that's
also zero at
the critical point. So, that term also goes
away.
OK, so linear approximation is really no good.
We need more terms. So, what are the next
terms?
Well, the next terms are quadratic terms,
and so I mean, if you remember the Taylor
formula for a function of a single variable,
there was the derivative times x minus x0
plus one half of a
second derivative times x-x0^2. And see, this
side here is
really Taylor approximation in one variable
looking only at x.
But of course, we also have terms involving
y,
and terms involving simultaneously x and y.
And, these terms are fxy times change in x
times change in y
plus one half of fyy(y-y0)^2. There's no one
half in the
middle because, in fact, you would have two
terms, one for xy, one for yx, but they are
the
same. And then, if you want to
continue, there is actually cubic terms involving
the third
derivatives, and so on, but we are not actually
looking
at them. And so, now,
when we do this approximation, well, the type
of critical
point remains the same when we replace the
function by this
approximation. And so, we can apply the
argument that we used to deduce things in
the quadratic case.
In fact, it still works in the general case
using this
approximation formula.
So --
The general case reduces to
the quadratic case.
And now, you see actually why, well, here
you see,
again, how this coefficient which we used
to call little a
is also one half of capital A. And same here:
this coefficient is what we call capital B
or little b,
and this coefficient here is what we called
little c or one
half of capital C. And then, when you replace
these into the various cases that we had here,
you end up with the second derivative test.
So, what about the degenerate case?
Why can't we just say, well, it's going to
be a
degenerate critical point? So, the reason
is that this
approximation formula is reasonable only if
the higher
order terms are negligible. OK, so in fact,
secretly, there's more terms. This is only
an approximation.
There would be terms involving third derivatives,
and maybe even beyond that. And, so it is
not to generate
case, they don't actually matter
because the shape of the function,
the shape of the graph, is actually determined
by the
quadratic terms. But, in the degenerate case,
see, if I start with this and I add something
even very,
very small along the y axis, then that can
be enough to bend
this very slightly up or slightly down,
and turn my degenerate point in to either
a minimum or a saddle
point. And, I won't be able to tell
until I go further in the list of derivatives.
So, in the degenerate case, what actually
happens depends
on the higher order derivatives.
So, we will need to analyze things more carefully.
Well, we're not going to bother with that
in this class.
So, we'll just say, well, we cannot compute,
OK? I mean, you have to realize
that in real life, you have to be extremely
unlucky for this quantity to end up being
exactly 0.
[LAUGHTER] Well, if that happens,
then what you should do is maybe try by inspection.
See if there's a good reason why the function
should always
be positive or always be negative, or something.
Or, you know, plot it on a computer and see
what happens. But, otherwise we can't compute.
OK, so let's do an example. So, probably I
should leave
this on so that we still have the test with
us.
And, instead, OK, so I'll do my example here.
OK, so just an example. Let's look at f of
(x,
y) = x y 1/xy, where x and y are positive.
So, I'm looking only at the first quadrant.
OK, I mean, I'm doing this because I don't
want the
denominator to become zero. So, I'm just looking
at the
situation. So, let's look first for,
so, the question will be, what are the minimum
and
maximum of this function? So, the first thing
we should
do to answer this question is look for critical
points,
OK? So, for that,
we have to compute the first derivatives.
OK, so fx is one minus one over x^2y, OK?
Take the derivative of one over x, that's
negative one over x^2.
And, we'll want to set that equal to zero.
And fy is one minus one over xy^2.
And, we want to set that equal to zero.
So, what are the equations we have to solve?
Well, I guess x^2y equals one, I mean, if
I move this guy over
here I get one over x^2y equals one.
That's x^2y equals one, and xy^2 equals one.
What do you get by comparing these two?
Well, x and y should both be, OK, so yeah,
I agree with you that one and one is a solution.
Why is it the only one? So, first, if I divide
this one
by that one, I get x over y equals one.
So, it tells me x equals y. And then, if x
equals y,
then if I put that into here, it will give
me y^3 equals one,
which tells me y equals one, and therefore,
x equals one as well. OK, so, there's only
one
solution. There's only one critical
point, which is going to be (1,1).
OK, so, now here's where you do a bit of work.
What do you think of that critical point?
OK, I see some valid votes. I see some, OK,
I see a lot of people answering four.
[LAUGHTER] that seems to suggest that
maybe you haven't completed the second derivative
yet.
Yes, I see someone giving the correct answer.
I see some people not giving quite the correct
answer.
I see more and more correct answers.
OK, so let's see. To figure out what type
of
point is, we should compute the second partial
derivatives.
So, fxx is, what do we get what we take the
derivative of this
with respect to x? Two over x^3y, OK?
So, at our point, a will be 2. Fxy will be
one over x^2y^2.
So, B will be one. And, Fyy is going to be
two
over xy^3. So, C will be two.
And so that tells us, well, AC-B^2 is four
minus one.
Sorry, I should probably use a different blackboard
for that.
AC-B2 is two times two minus 1^2 is three.
It's positive. That tells us we are either
a
local minimum or local maximum. And, A is
positive.
So, it's a local minimum. And, in fact,
you can check it's the global minimum.
What about the maximum? Well, if a maximum
is not
actually at a critical point, it's on the
boundary,
or at infinity. See, so we have actually to
check what happens when x and y go to zero
or to infinity.
Well, if that happens, if x or y goes to infinity,
then the function goes to infinity.
Also, if x or y goes to zero, then one over
xy goes to
infinity. So, the maximum,
well, the function goes to infinity when x
goes to infinity
or y goes to infinity, or x and y go to zero.
So, it's not at a critical point.
OK, so, in general, we have to check both
the
critical points and the boundaries to decide
what
happens. OK, the end.
Have a nice weekend.