The following content is provided under a
Creative
Commons license. Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to offer high quality
educational
resources for free. To make a donation or
to view
additional materials from hundreds of MIT
courses,
visit MIT OpenCourseWare at ocw.mit.edu.
Let me start by basically listing the main
things we have
learned over the past three weeks or so.
And I will add a few complements of information
about
that because there are a few small details
that I didn't
quite clarify and that I should probably make
a bit clearer,
especially what happened at the very end of
yesterday's class.
Here is a list of things that should be on
your review sheet
for the exam. The first thing we learned
about, the main topic of this unit is about
functions of
several variables. We have learned how to
think of
functions of two or three variables in terms
of plotting
them. In particular,
well, not only the graph but also the contour
plot and how to
read a contour plot. And we have learned how
to
study variations of these functions using
partial
derivatives. Remember, we have defined the
partial of f with respect to some variable,
say, x to be the rate of change with respect
to x when we hold
all the other variables constant.
If you have a function of x and y, this symbol
means you
differentiate with respect to x treating y
as a constant.
And we have learned how to package partial
derivatives into
a vector,the gradient vector. For example,
if we have a function of three variables,
the vector whose
components are the partial derivatives.
And we have seen how to use the gradient vector
or the partial
derivatives to derive various things such
as approximation
formulas. The change in f,
when we change x, y, z slightly,
is approximately equal to, well, there are
several terms.
And I can rewrite this in vector form as the
gradient dot
product the amount by which the position vector
has changed.
Basically, what causes f to change is that
I am changing x,
y and z by small amounts and how sensitive
f is to each
variable is precisely what the partial derivatives
measure.
And, in particular, this approximation is
called
the tangent plane approximation because it
tells us,
in fact, it amounts to identifying the
graph of the function with its tangent plane.
It means that we assume that the function
depends more or
less linearly on x, y and z.
And, if we set these things equal, what we
get is actually,
we are replacing the function by its linear
approximation.
We are replacing the graph by its tangent
plane.
Except, of course, we haven't see the graph
of a
function of three variables because that would
live in
4-dimensional space. So, when we think of
a graph,
really, it is a function of two variables.
That also tells us how to find tangent planes
to level
surfaces.
Recall that the tangent plane to a surface,
given by the equation f of x, y, z equals
z,
at a given point can be found by looking first
for its normal
vector. And we know that the normal
vector is actually, well,
one normal vector is given by the gradient
of a function
because we know that the gradient is actually
pointing
perpendicularly to the level sets towards
higher values of a
function. And it gives us the direction
of fastest increase of a function.
OK. Any questions about these
topics? No.
OK. Let me add, actually,
a cultural note to what we have seen so far
about partial
derivatives and how to use them, which is
maybe something I
should have mentioned a couple of weeks ago.
Why do we like partial derivatives?
Well, one obvious reason is we can do all
these things.
But another reason is that, really,
you need partial derivatives to do physics
and to understand
much of the world that is around you because
a lot of things
actually are governed by what is called partial
differentiation
equations.
So if you want a cultural remark about what
this is good
for. A partial differential equation
is an equation that involves the partial derivatives
of a
function. So you have some function that
is unknown that depends on a bunch of variables.
And a partial differential equation is some
relation
between its partial derivatives. Let me see.
These are equations involving the partial
derivatives -- --
of
an unknown function. Let me give you an example
to
see how that works. For example,
the heat equation is one example of a partial
differential equation. It is the equation
-- Well,
let me write for you the space version of
it.
It is the equation partial f over partial
t equals some
constant times the sum of the second partials
with respect to
x, y and z. So this is an equation where we
are trying to solve for a function f that
depends,
actually, on four variables, x, y, z, t.
And what should you have in mind?
Well, this equation governs temperature.
If you think that f of x, y, z, t will be
the temperature at a
point in space at position x, y, z and at
time t,
then this tells you how temperature changes
over time.
It tells you that at any given point,
the rate of change of temperature over time
is given
by this complicated expression in the partial
derivatives in
terms of the space coordinates x, y, z.
If you know, for example, the initial distribution
of
temperature in this room, and if you assume
that nothing
is generating heat or taking heat away,
so if you don't have any air conditioning
or heating going
on, then it will tell you how the
temperature will change over time and eventually
stabilize to
some final value. Yes?
Why do we take the partial derivative twice?
Well, that is a question, I would say,
for a physics person. But in a few weeks we
will
actually see a derivation of where this equation
comes from
and try to justify it. But, really,
that is something you will see in a physics
class.
The reason for that is basically physics of
how heat is
transported between particles in fluid, or
actually any medium.
This constant k actually is called the heat
conductivity.
It tells you how well the heat flows through
the material that
you are looking at. Anyway, I am giving it
to you
just to show you an example of a real life
problem where,
in fact, you have to solve one of these things.
Now, how to solve partial differential equations
is not a
topic for this class. It is not even a topic
for
18.03 which is called Differential Equations,
without partial, which means there actually
you
will learn tools to study and solve these
equations but when
there is only one variable involved.
And you will see it is already quite hard.
And, if you want more on that one, we have
many fine classes
about partial differential equations.
But one thing at a time. I wanted to point
out to you
that very often functions that you see in
real life satisfy
many nice relations between the partial derivatives.
That was in case you were wondering why on
the syllabus
for today it said partial differential equations.
Now we have officially covered the topic.
That is basically all we need to know about
it.
But we will come back to that a bit later.
You will see. OK.
If there are no further questions, let me
continue and
go back to my list of topics. Oh, sorry.
I should have written down that this equation
is solved by
temperature for point x, y, z at time t.
OK. And there are, actually,
many other interesting partial differential
equations you will
maybe sometimes learn about the wave equation
that governs how
waves propagate in space, about the diffusion
equation,
when you have maybe a mixture of two fluids,
how they somehow mix over time and so on.
Basically, to every problem you might want
to consider there is
a partial differential equation to solve.
OK. Anyway. Sorry. Back to my list of topics.
One important application we have seen of
partial derivatives
is to try to optimize things, try to solve
minimum/maximum
problems.
Remember that we have introduced the notion
of
critical points of a function. A critical
point is when all
the partial derivatives are zero.
And then there are various kinds of critical
points.
There is maxima and there is minimum, but
there is also
saddle points. And we have seen a method using
second derivatives -- --
to decide which kind of critical
point we have. I should say that is for a
function of two variables to try to decide
whether a given
critical point is a minimum, a maximum or
a saddle point.
And we have also seen that actually that is
not enough to
find the minimum of a maximum of a function
because the minimum
of a maximum could occur on the boundary.
Just to give you a small reminder,
when you have a function of one variables,
if you are trying to find the minimum and
the maximum of a
function whose graph looks like this,
well, you are going to tell me, quite obviously,
that the maximum is this point up here.
And that is a point where the first derivative
is zero.
That is a critical point. And we used the
second
derivative to see that this critical point
is a local
maximum. But then, when we are looking
for the minimum of a function, well, it is
not at a critical
point. It is actually here at the
boundary of the domain, you know, the range
of values
that we are going to consider. Here the minimum
is at the
boundary. And the maximum is at a
critical point. Similarly, when you have a
function of several variables, say of two
variables,
for example, then the minimum and the
maximum will be achieved either at a critical
point.
And then we can use these methods to find
where they are.
Or, somewhere on the boundary of a set of
values that are
allowed. It could be that we actually
achieve a minimum by making x and y as small
as possible.
Maybe letting them go to zero if they had
to be positive or
maybe by making them go to infinity.
So, we have to keep our minds open and look
at various
possibilities. We are going to do a problem
like that. We are going to go over a
practice problem from the practice test to
clarify this.
Another important cultural application of
minimum/maximum
problems in two variables that we have seen
in class is the
least squared method to find the best fit
line,
or the best fit anything, really,
to find when you have a set of data points
what is the best
linear approximately for these data points.
And here I have some good news for you.
While you should definitely know what this
is about,
it will not be on the test.
[APPLAUSE] That doesn't mean that you
should forget everything we have seen about
it,
OK? Now what is next on my list of
topics? We have seen differentials.
Remember the differential of f, by definition,
would be this kind of quantity. At first it
looks just like a
new way to package partial derivatives together
into some
new kind of object. Now, what is this good
for?
Well, it is a good way to remember approximation
formulas.
It is a good way to also study how variations
in x,
y, z relate to variations in f. In particular,
we can divide this by variations,
actually, by dx or by dy or by dz in any situation
that we
want, or by d of some other variable
to get chain rules. The chain rule says,
for example, there are many situations.
But, for example, if x, y and z depend on
some
other variable, say of variables maybe even
u
and v, then that means that f becomes
a function of u and v. And then we can ask
ourselves,
how sensitive is f to a value of u?
Well, we can answer that. The chain rule is
something
like this. And let me explain to you again
where this comes from. Basically, what this
quantity
means is if we change u and keep v constant,
what happens to the
value of f? Well, why would the value of f
change in the first place when f is just a
function of x,
y, z and not directly of you? Well, it changes
because x,
y and z depend on u. First we have to figure
out how
quickly x, y and z change when we change u.
Well, how quickly they do that is precisely
partial x over
partial u, partial y over partial u, partial
z over
partial u. These are the rates of change
of x, y, z when we change u. And now, when
we change x,
y and z, that causes f to change.
How much does f change? Well, partial f over
partial x
tells us how quickly f changes if I just change
x.
I get this. That is the change in f caused
just by the fact that x changes when u changes.
But then y also changes. y changes at this
rate.
And that causes f to change at that rate.
And z changes as well, and that causes f to
change at
that rate. And the effects add up together.
Does that make sense? OK.
And so, in particular, we can use the chain
rule to do
changes of variables. If we have, say,
a function in terms of polar coordinates on
theta and we like
to switch it to rectangular coordinates x
and y then we can
use chain rules to relate the partial derivatives.
And finally, last but not least,
we have seen how to deal with non-independent
variables.
When our variables say x, y, z related by
some equation.
One way we can deal with this is to solve
for one of the
variables and go back to two independent variables,
but we cannot always do that. Of course, on
the exam,
you can be sure that I will make sure that
you cannot solve
for a variable you want to remove because
that would be too
easy. Then when we have to look at
all of them, we will have to take into account
this relation,
we have seen two useful methods.
One of them is to find the minimum of a maximum
of a
function when the variables are not independent,
and that is the method of Lagrange multipliers.
Remember, to
find the minimum or the maximum of the function
f, subject to the constraint
g
equals constant, well, we write down equations
that say that the gradient of f is actually
proportional to the
gradient of g. There is a new variable here,
lambda, the multiplier. And so, for example,
well, I guess here I had functions of three
variables,
so this becomes three equations.
f sub x equals lambda g sub x, f sub y equals
lambda g sub y,
and f sub z equals lambda g sub z.
And, when we plug in the formulas for f and
g,
well, we are left with three equations involving
the four
variables, x, y, z and lambda.
What is wrong? Well, we don't have actually
four independent variables. We also have this
relation,
whatever the constraint was relating x, y
and z together.
Then we can try to solve this. And, depending
on the
situation, it is sometimes easy. And it sometimes
it is very
hard or even impossible. But on the test,
I haven't decided yet, but it could well be
that the
problem about Lagrange multipliers just asks
you to
write the equations and not to solve them.
[APPLAUSE] Well, I don't know yet.
I am not promising anything. But, before you
start solving,
check whether the problem asks you to solve
them or not.
If it doesn't then probably you shouldn't.
Another topic that we solved just yesterday
is constrained
partial derivatives. And I guess I have to
re-explain a little bit because my guess is
that things were not
extremely clear at the end of class yesterday.
Now we are in the same situation.
We have a function, let's say, f of x,
y, z where variables x, y and z are not independent
but
are constrained by some relation of this form.
Some quantity involving x, y and z is equal
to maybe zero
or some other constant. And then, what we
want to know,
is what is the rate of change of f with respect
to one of the
variables, say, x, y or z when I keep the
others constant? Well, I cannot keep all the
other constant because that would not be compatible
with
this condition. I mean that would be the usual
or so-called formal partial derivative of
f ignoring the
constraint. To take this into account means
that if we vary one variable while keeping
another one fixed
then the third one, since it depends on them,
must also change somehow. And we must take
that into
account. Let's say, for example,
we want to find -- I am going to do a different
example from
yesterday. So, if you really didn't like
that one, you don't have to see it again.
Let's say that we want to find the partial
derivative of f with
respect to z keeping y constant. What does
that mean?
That means y is constant, z varies and x somehow
is
mysteriously a function of y and z for this
equation.
And then, of course because it depends on
y,
that means x will vary. Sorry, depends on
y and z and z
varies. Now we are asking ourselves
what is the rate of change of f with respect
to z in this
situation?
And so we have two methods to do that.
Let me start with the one with differentials
that hopefully you
kind of understood yesterday, but if not here
is a second
chance. Using differentials means that
we will try to express df in terms of dz in
this particular
situation. What do we know about df in
general? Well, we know that df is f sub
x dx plus f sub y dy plus f sub z dz.
That is the general statement. But, of course,
we are in a special case. We are in a special
case where
first y is constant. y is constant means that
we can
set dy to be zero. This goes away and becomes
zero.
The second thing is actually we don't care
about x.
We would like to get rid of x because it is
this dependent
variable. What we really want to do is
express df only in terms of dz. What we need
is to relate dx
with dz. Well, to do that,
we need to look at how the variables are related
so we need
to look at the constraint g. Well, how do
we do that?
We look at the differential g. So dg is g
sub x dx plus g sub
y dy plus g sub z dz. And that is zero because
we are
setting g to always stay constant.
So, g doesn't change. If g doesn't change
then we
have a relation between dx, dy and dz.
Well, in fact, we say we are going to look
only at the case where y is constant.
y doesn't change and this becomes zero.
Well, now we have a relation between dx and
dz.
We know how x depends on z. And when we know
how x depends
on z, we can plug that into here and get how
f depends on z.
Let's do that.
Again, saying that g cannot change and keeping
y constant
tells us g sub x dx plus g sub z dz is zero
and we would like to
solve for dx in terms of dz. That tells us
dx should be
minus g sub z dz divided by g sub x.
If you want, this is the rate of change of
x
with respect to z when we keep y constant.
In our new terminology this is partial x over
partial z with y
held constant. This is the rate of change
of x
with respect to z. Now, when we know that,
we are going to plug that into this equation.
And that will tell us that df is f sub x times
dx.
Well, what is dx? dx is now minus g sub z
over g
sub x dz plus f sub z dz. So that will be
minus fx g sub
z over g sub x plus f sub z times dz.
And so this coefficient here is the rate of
change of f with
respect to z in the situation we are considering.
This quantity is what we call partial f over
partial z with y
held constant. That is what we wanted to find.
Now, let's see another way to do the same
calculation and then
you can choose which one you prefer.
The other method is using the chain rule.
We use the chain rule to understand how f
depends on z
when y is held constant. Let me first try
the chain rule
brutally and then we will try to analyze what
is going on.
You can just use the version that I have up
there as a
template to see what is going on, but I am
going to explain it
more carefully again.
That is the most mechanical and mindless way
of writing down the
chain rule. I am just saying here that I am
varying z, keeping y constant, and I want
to know how f
changes. Well, f might change because x
might change, y might change and z might
change. Now, how quickly does x change?
Well, the rate of change of x in this situation
is partial x,
partial z with y held constant. If I change
x at this rate then
f will change at that rate. Now, y might change,
so the rate of change of y would be the rate
of change of y
with respect to z holding y constant.
Wait a second. If y is held constant then
y
doesn't change. So, actually,
this guy is zero and you didn't really have
to write that term.
But I wrote it just to be systematic.
If y had been somehow able to change at a
certain rate then
that would have caused f to change at that
rate.
And, of course, if y is held constant then
nothing happens here. Finally, while z is
changing at
a certain rate, this rate is this one and
that
causes f to change at that rate. And then
we add the effects
together. See, it is nothing but the
good-old chain rule. Just I have put these
extra
subscripts to tell us what is held constant
and what isn't.
Now, of course we can simplify it a little
bit more.
Because, here, how quickly does z change if
I
am changing z? Well, the rate of change of
z,
with respect to itself, is just one.
In fact, the really mysterious part of this
is the one here,
which is the rate of change of x with respect
to z.
And, to find that, we have to understand the
constraint. How can we find the rate of
change of x with respect to z? Well, we could
use
differentials, like we did here,
but we can also keep using the chain rule.
How can I do that? Well, I can just look at
how g
would change with respect to z when y is held
constant.
I just do the same calculation with g instead
of f.
But, before I do it, let's ask ourselves first
what
is this equal to. Well, if g is held constant
then, when we vary z keeping y constant and
changing x,
well, g still doesn't change. It is held constant.
In fact, that should be zero. But, if we just
say that,
we are not going to get to that.
Let's see how we can compute that using the
chain rule.
Well, the chain rule tells us g changes because
x,
y and z change. How does it change because
of x?
Well, partial g over partial x times the rate
of change of x.
How does it change because of y? Well, partial
g over partial y
times the rate of change of y. But, of course,
if you are smarter than me then you don't
need to actually write
this one because y is held constant.
And then there is the rate of change because
z changes.
And how quickly z changes here, of course,
is one.
Out of this you get, well, I am tired of writing
partial g over partial x. We can just write
g sub x times
partial x over partial z y constant plus g
sub z.
And now we found how x depends on z.
Partial x over partial z with y held constant
is negative g sub
z over g sub x. Now we plug that into that
and
we get our answer. It goes all the way up
here.
And then we get the answer. I am not going
to,
well, I guess I can write it again.
There was partial f over partial x times this
guy,
minus g sub z over g sub x, plus partial f
over partial z.
And you can observe that this is exactly the
same formula that
we had over here. In fact, let's compare this
to
make it side by side. I claim we did exactly
the same
thing, just with different notations.
If you take the differential of f and you
divide it by dz in
this situation where y is held constant and
so on,
you get exactly this chain rule up there.
That chain rule up there is this guy, df,
divided by dz with y held constant.
And the term involving dy was replaced by
zero on both sides
because we knew, actually, that y is held
constant. Now, the real difficulty in
both cases comes from dx. And what we do about
dx is we
use the constant. Here we use it by writing
dg
equals zero. Here we write the chain rule
for g, which is the same thing, just divided
by dz with y held
constant. This formula or that formula
are the same, just divided by dz with y held
constant. And then, in both cases,
we used that to solve for dx. And then we
plugged into the
formula of df to express df over dz, or partial
f,
partial z with y held constant. So, the two
methods are pretty
much the same. Quick poll.
Who prefers this one? Who prefers that one?
OK. Majority vote seems to be for
differentials, but it doesn't mean that it
is
better. Both are fine.
You can use whichever one you want.
But you should give both a try. OK. Any questions?
Yes? Yes. Thank you.
I forgot to mention it. Where did that go?
I think I erased that part. We need to know
-- --
directional derivatives. Pretty much the only
thing to
remember about them is that df over ds,
in the direction of some unit vector u,
is just the gradient f dot product with u.
That is pretty much all we know about them.
Any other topics that I forgot to list?
No. Yes?
Can I erase three boards at a time?
No, I would need three hands to do that.
I think what we should do now is look quickly
at the practice
test. I mean, given the time,
you will mostly have to think about it yourselves.
Hopefully you have a copy of the practice
exam.
The first problem is a simple problem.
Find the gradient. Find an approximation formula.
Hopefully you know how to do that.
The second problem is one about writing a
contour plot.
And so, before I let you go for the weekend,
I want to make sure
that you actually know how to read a contour
plot.
One thing I should mention is this problem
asks you to
estimate partial derivatives by writing a
contour plot.
We have not done that, so that will not actually
be on
the test. We will be doing qualitative
questions like what is the sine of a partial
derivative.
Is it zero, less than zero or more than zero?
You don't need to bring a ruler to estimate
partial derivatives
the way that this problem asks you to.
[APPLAUSE] Let's look at problem 2B.
Problem 2B is asking you to find the point
at which h equals
2200, partial h over partial x equals
zero and partial h over partial y is less
than zero.
Let's try and see what is going on here.
A point where f equals 2200, well, that should
be probably
on the level curve that says 2200.
We can actually zoom in. Here is the level
2200.
Now I want partial h over partial x to be
zero.
That means if I change x, keeping y constant,
the value of h doesn't change. Which points
on the level curve
satisfy that property? It is the top and the
bottom.
If you are here, for example, and you move
in the x
direction, well, you see,
as you get to there from the left,
the height first increases and then decreases.
It goes for a maximum at that point.
So, at that point, the partial derivative
is zero
with respect to x. And the same here.
Now, let's find partial h over partial y less
than zero.
That means if we go north we should go down.
Well, which one is it, top or bottom?
Top. Yes. Here, if you go north,
then you go from 2200 down to 2100.
This is where the point is. Now, the problem
here was also
asking you to estimate partial h over partial
y.
And if you were curious how you would do that,
well, you would try to figure out how long
it takes before you
reach the next level curve. To go from here
to here,
to go from Q to this new point, say Q prime,
the change in y, well, you would have to read
the scale, which was down here,
would be about something like 300.
What is the change in height when you go from
Q to Q prime?
Well, you go down from 2200 to 2100.
That is actually minus 100 exactly.
OK? And so delta h over delta y is
about minus one-third, well, minus 100 over
300 which
is
minus one-third. And that is an approximation
for partial derivative. So, that is how you
would do it.
Now, let me go back to other things.
If you look at this practice exam, basically
there is a bit
of everything and it is kind of fairly representative
of what
might happen on Tuesday. There will be a mix
of easy
problems and of harder problems. Expect something
about
computing gradients, approximations,
rate of change. Expect a problem about reading
a contour plot. Expect one about a min/max
problem, something about Lagrange
multipliers, something about the chain rule
and something about constrained partial derivatives.
I mean pretty much all the topics are going
to be there.